<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of Isuf Bassa, captain general of the Ottoman army at the invasion of Candia</title>
            <author>Higgons, Thomas, Sir, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 110 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34466</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14447367</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14447367</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43757)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1060:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of Isuf Bassa, captain general of the Ottoman army at the invasion of Candia</title>
                  <author>Higgons, Thomas, Sir, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 196, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Kettlewel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Higgons.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Yeusuf, --  Pasha.</term>
               <term>Heevakleion (Crete) --  Siege, 1667-1669.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF Iſuf Baſſa CAPTAIN GENERAL OF THE Ottoman Army At the Invaſion of CANDIA.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Kettlewel,</hi> at the Hand and Scepter over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe Novels and Romances of theſe times by mixing real things with Fiction, have ſo corrupted Hiſtory, that it is hard to diſtinguiſh Truth from Fable. Nor is it onely the Greek and Roman Story which have been ſo ſerved, but the Turkiſh too. For as we have had
<pb facs="tcp:102362:3"/>
a Grand Cyrus and a Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra, ſo there is an Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Baſſa; the Authors of all which have proſtituted Truth, to give colour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability to their Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But in this Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Reader, I aſſure you there is not any thing of that kind. All here is matter of fact, taken either out of approved Hiſtories, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Letters and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Life of Iſuf Baſſa, which is full of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Events, you have
<pb facs="tcp:102362:3"/>
here the beginning of the War of Candia, of which he was a great occaſion. Nor have you onely the Succeſſes of that War, but the Cauſes of it, and the Motives upon which it was undertaken. A War as memorable certainly as hath been in any Age, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you conſider the duration of it, which was Four and twenty years; or the numbers of Men which periſhed in it, of which there is an account of above Nine hundred thouſand onely of the Turkiſh ſide, who were buryed in the
<pb facs="tcp:102362:4"/>
Fields and in the Seas of Candia; or the diſparity of the Forces betwixt which that War was made; a great part of the power of Europe, Africa, and Aſia, being engaged againſt the ſingle State of Venice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 19. line 5. for Ports read Poſts. p. 20. l. 18. read and overcame. p. 47. l. 17. for Diſcovering read Diſſerving. p. 58. l. 20. for Officers read others. p. 60. l. 7. for Court read Covent, l. 10. read Alviſi. p. 78. l. 16. for Naris read Nani. p. 89. l. 16. read was. p. 118. l. 6. read Cernide. p. 151. l. 4. for ſo read to. p. 156. l. laſt dele out He. p. 158 l. 16. read Selectar.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102362:5"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF ISUF BASSA.</head>
            <div n="1-30" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Province of Dalmatia, upon the Confines of the State of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, liv'd a young man called Iſuf Vaſcouich, meanly born, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poor; but having a great heart, and impatient of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Condition, he reſolved
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102362:6"/>
to put himſelf into the World, and try what Fortune would do for him.</p>
               <p>He ſet out of his Father's Houſe in ſo ill equipage, that before he had gone far, his feet were all cut with the ſtones: which moved an old woman, who was touched with pity to ſee a handſome Youth in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to give him a pair of Shooes; a kindneſs which in due time he amply requited. Iſuf (for by that name he was afterwards known) came firſt to Nadin in Croatia, where having ſome knowledge of the Turkiſh Tongue, he put himſelf in the ſervice of Sinan Bey, one of the Governours of that Country, as a helper in the Stables: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102362:6"/>
taken notice of for a youth of more than an ordinary Wit, he was perſwaded by a Capigi, who was going to the Court, to get his Congé of Sinan Bey, and to accompany him to Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, the place for men to ſeek for Fortunes. Coming to the Seraglio, the beſt Imployment he could get, was, to cleave Wood for the Grand Seignior's Kitchin; from which in a little time he was advanced to carry Water into the Garden, and admitted there as an under-Gardner; a Poſt of all inferiour ones the moſt advantageous, ſince the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour paſſeth much time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe people, and often calls his Councils of State and War into his Gardens; by which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102362:7"/>
means thoſe Gardners come ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all the Grandees of the Court, and are known to the Sultan himſelf; who having no Hereditary Nobility, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth many times the meaneſt of his Slaves to the moſt eminent Dignities of the Empire.</p>
               <p>It hapned that Iſuf came into this Employment much about the time that Sultan Amurat went for Babylon; who before he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his Journey, ſent for his three Brothers, Orcan, Bajazet, and Ibrahim, one after another; and diſcourſing to them of the Expedition he was undertaking, did what he could to ſound their inclinations: and finding that Orcan and Bajazet deſired Arms and Horſes, that they might
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102362:7"/>
wait upon his Majeſty to the War, he thought it not ſafe to leave ſuch young men behind him; and ſo commanded that they ſhould both be ſtrangled. But Ibrahim, who innocently, or rather, as it is thought, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Sultaneſs his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, asked nothing of him but a few Aſpers to buy Cages to put his Birds in, was left alive; but out of all capacity to make any diſturbance in the abſence of his Brother, being put under a ſtrict Guard in one of the Towers of the Seraglio, where he had no creature to ſerve him but a woman-Negro, a Mute. In this Tower there was a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow which looked into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den where Iſuf uſed to water the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102362:8"/>
Flowers; from whence Ibrahim would often peep through a Grate upon him, and liſten to him as he ſung, ſeeming delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Muſick of his Voice. Iſuf perceiving he was taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of by Ibrahim, and having compaſſion for this miſerable Prince, would at certain times when no body obſerved him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Tower, and tell Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him all the news of the Court, regaling him with ſuch Flowers and Fruits as were in the Garden. Ibrahim finding that Iſuf was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſerve him, and thinking him diſcreet, deſired him, if he wiſhed him well, as he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that he would talk no more at the Grate, ſince if it were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, it might be the loſs of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102362:8"/>
both their lives. <hi>But</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when you have any thing to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to me, ſing it in a tune as you paſs under my window; which I ſhall underſtand as well as if you ſpoke.</hi> By which means Ibrahim came to know all that paſſed in the Seraglio, and whatever ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the Army.</p>
               <p>Amurat was now upon his march to beſiege Babylon, when advice was brought him that the King of Perſia had taken the Field with one hundred and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe, and was incam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped ſome leagues from Babylon, in a vaſt and fertile plain, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with Forage and Proviſion; where he ſtayed to countenance the Beſieged, and to be ready upon occaſion to give them ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102362:9"/>Old Babylon was built by Queen Semiramis, upon both ſides the Euphrates, which cuts it in two; and was the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis of the Aſſyrian Empire, and one of the ſeven Miracles of the World: But out of its ruines is ariſen another Babylon, called Bagdet by the Turks, which ſtands not upon Euphrates, but fifty miles off, upon the River Tigris, which runs into Euphrates. This City is very vaſt, divided by the Tigris, and incompaſſed with an ancient Wall with ſome Half-Moons about it. But its chief ſtrength conſiſted in three great Ditches, and in the number and reſolution of the Defendants; of which were forty thouſand Gariſon-Souldiers, and as many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102362:9"/>
Inhabitants bearing Arms, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Gunners and Enginiers, who came from ſeveral parts of Chriſtendom to ſerve the Perſian.</p>
               <p>Upon the news of Amurat's marching, the King of Perſia commanded the Suburbs of the City to be levelled with the ground, and put the place into the beſt condition it was capable of to receive ſo formidable an Enemy. And that he might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit nothing to ſtop this Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation which threatned to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm Aſia, he ſent an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour to Amurat with rich Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, to ſue for Peace. But the Tyrant commanded, if the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour did not offer the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Babylon, that they ſhould cut off his Noſe and Ears.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102362:10"/>
This the Grand Viſir diſſwaded, as an indignity not to be done to the Miniſter of ſo great a Prince, and one of their own Religion. The Preſent was moſt magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent which the Ambaſſadour brought: Eight Mules laden, forty Dromedaries cover'd with cloth of Silk and Gold, eight Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Horſes with rich Houſſes, eighteen Carpets of Silk and Seven of Gold, two hundred and forty Veſts of Brocado and Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, two hundred pieces of the fineſt Porcellain, forty Sable Skins, nine Perſian Bows with Arrows of moſt exquiſite work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, great quantities of Musk and Amber-greece, and twenty five Bayls of Linnen painted. Beſides, the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102362:10"/>
preſented the Emperour with divers delicious Drinks, as the moſt acceptable things to a man ſo debauched and vitious; and laſt of all, the Alchoran written upon Silken paper, which the Grand Seignior in reverence kiſſed.</p>
               <p>Hardly had the Ambaſſadour expoſed his Preſents, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Credentials, but he was ſurrounded with Guards, and carryed Priſoner to his own Houſe; contrary to the Faith given him, and to the Law of Nations. But Amurat gave him to underſtand, that he would carry him back into Perſia him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; who to increaſe his Army, had made ſix thouſand new Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries, though he had decreed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102362:11"/>
a little before, that their number ſhould not upon any pretence be augmented. And to ſweeten their Order, which he had much exaſperated, and to oblige them for the future, he dreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the habit of a Janizary, and marched ſo all his Journey in the head of his Army. Nor was his care leſs of his other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia's: for he appeared perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the Muſters of his Timars, to ſee that no man upon pain of death ſhould decline the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And becauſe the General of the Ordnance ſeemed to make ſome difficulty of getting along four vaſt pieces of Cannon, by reaſon of the badneſs of the way, he immediately cauſed his head to be ſtruck off. So that after
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102362:11"/>
that, no creature durſt interpoſe the leaſt obſtacle or delay to the executing of Amurat's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Seeing Conſervatories of Snow, which were to refreſh his Wine, he would not let them be filled; ſaying, he would have nothing of Luxury or Delicacy in his Camp, and that he went not to carry Ice but Fire into Perſia. He commanded all the Takers of Tobacco who were in his Army to be fley'd alive, and to be left expoſed upon the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for an example. His chief Phyſician, a man learned in the Perſian and Arabian Tongues, making him a relation of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable effects of Opium, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to take ſo great a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of it himſelf, that he dyed within a few hours.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102362:12"/>All the way that Amurat went, his Army augmented, upon the arrival of new Sangiachs, who all left their Governments to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Sultan; who though he met with many diſaſters in his march, endured all with an invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible patience. As he croſſed the Euphrates, the Bridge over which he paſſed his Army broke, not able to bear the weight which was upon it: Baggage, Horſes, Camels, and many Souldiers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwallowed by the water, ſwoln with the rains which were lately fallen. Beſides this, a mortality reigned in his Army, which carryed away his Souldiers every day. But no misfortune could deject Amurat, or retard his progreſs. The difficulties he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102362:12"/>
encounter'd did but whet his Courage: and, as if he were ſure of conquering, he made a Vow that he would not change his clothes till he was in Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</p>
               <p>But though his heart was ſo much ſet upon this enterprize, he often thought of the ſtate of his Affairs at home; and fearing Changes in his abſence, repented him of the humanity which he had ſhewed his Brother Ibrahim; and therefore diſpatched away one of his Baſſa's to Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, with orders to ſee him ſtrangled. The Baſſa could not come ſo ſecretly into the Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio, but it was diſcovered by ſome of the Sultana's; who ſuſpecting the cauſe of his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102362:13"/>
and having pity for Ibrahim, the only Prince left of the Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Line, would not let the Baſſa touch him; but drove him out of the Seraglio in ſuch haſte, that he hardly eſcaped to carry the news to his Maſter. Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, though his heart boyled with rage for this Affront, did not think it a time to revenge it; but ſuppreſſing his reſentment till his return, continued his march with moſt indefatigable pains; and the Ninth of November, in the year 1638, ſat down before Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</p>
               <p>Juſt before his arrival there, he was met by the Baſſa of Cairo with rich Preſents, and four and twenty thouſand Souldiers. And from Paleſtine and all the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102362:13"/>
Countrys came Recruits, which added conſiderably to the number of his formidable Army. About the ſame time came Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos King of Arabia, with his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Wife, and Son, to lay themſelves at Amurat's feet. He was courteouſly received by the chief Baſſa's, and feaſted after their manner. Thence he went to viſit the Grand Seignior; but whether he were doubtful of his ſafety, or repented him of his coming, it was obſerved that at his entring he grew very pale. But finding Amurat's Favourite there to receive him, he thought it a good Omen; and was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of apprehenſion, when he ſaw himſelf preſented with a Veſt of Cloth of Gold lined with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102362:14"/>
and a good purſe of Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quins, with thanks for the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance he had brought the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
               <p>All the Troops of that vaſt Army being joyned, there was a Council called, not onely of the chief Officers, but of the old Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries and Spahi's who had been in the Wars of Hungary, to have their opinions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the conducting of the Siege. After great debates, it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that an aſſault ſhould be made at one time in three pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: the firſt at the white Gate, under the Command of the Grand Viſir, with a Battery of twelve Cannon; the Second at the black Gate, by Muſtapha Baſſa, with a Battery of ten Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102362:14"/>
and the third at the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Gate, by Chuſſain Baſſa, Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerbeg of the leſſer Aſia, with eight pieces. Amurat viſited all the Ports himſelf, promiſing his Souldiers vaſt Donatives; and wrote to the Caimecan of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, that he ſhould order Prayers to be made throughout the Empire for his Succeſs, he being reſolved to conquer or to die. He put on plain clothes, that he might not be diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from other men; and that he might be preſent where dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger preſented it ſelf, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obſerved. His horſe ſtood always ready ſadled at the door of his Pavillon, that he might not loſe a moments time where there was occaſion for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102362:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Upon the opening of the Trenches, and the raiſing of the Batteries, he gave fire with his own hand to the firſt Gun; which was followed with a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious tempeſt of Canonades. In the beginning, the beſieged ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied out in groſs Squadrons; but being repulſed with great ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they grew more cautious. There was a bloody Conteſt one day to get a Half-moon; and it was hard to ſay whether the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors were leſs expert in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taquing, or the Beſieged in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending. But the Turks vaſt numbers ſupplied their defect of Skill, overcame all difficulties: ſo that they brought their Works to the edge of the ditch. And though their Mines had no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102362:15"/>
effect, the beſieged began to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of their Courage, being in deſpair of ſuccour. The Siege was carryed on more with Swords than Spades, ſince there being no Outworks, all was reduced to Aſſaults.</p>
               <p>Amurat was ſo tranſported with a deſire of carrying the place, that he would have led his men to the Breach himſelf, but that he was ſtay'd by his Captains, who repreſented to him the extremity of his danger; offering to precipitate themſelves, and ſacrifice their own lives, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he ſhould adventure his.</p>
               <p>Having paſſed the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Ditch, they met with deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate reſiſtance at the third; but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102362:16"/>
with multitudes of men they filled that too, and lodged upon it; ſo that now there was no defence remaining but the Wall, which, after they had made a breach in it of fifty yards long, they furiouſly aſſaulted. And here appeared a theatre of death, not onely in tempeſts of Shot, but ſhowrs of artificial Fire, Sulphur, and Bitumen. Both ſides fought for Life; the beſieged expecting no quarter if the place were taken, and the beſiegers no mercy from Amurat if they did not take it. On Chriſtmas-day the Turks made their laſt attempt, led on by Muſtapha Baſſa, whoſe men mounted the breach with greater bravery than it had been yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102362:16"/>
The Perſians with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual reſolution met them: and here began a Fight which was to decide the quarrel. As ſome men fell, new ones ſtill ſucceeded; the earth being dyed with blood, and covered with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes. At laſt the beſieged were forced to give ground, being quite tired; and the Turks ſtill re-inforced with freſh Recruits, climbed up the breach over heaps of bodies; and Muſtapha being the firſt who entered, with his own hand planted the Royal Standard in the City.</p>
               <p>In this Siege, of diſeaſes and wounds, there periſhed fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Turks, and above ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand were wounded. Of the Perſians, all the braveſt men fell;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102362:17"/>
onely ſome four and twenty thouſand, who ſurvived the ſlaughter, throwing down their Arms, were by Amurat's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand received to mercy. But Muſtapha offended at the cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of Amurat, perſwaded him to put them all to the ſword: remembring him how at Revan in Perſia, where he gave the Conquered Quarter, to requite his Mercy, as ſoon as his Army was gone, they roſe upon his Gariſon and cut them in pieces, and reſtored the City to the Perſian. This made Amurat, notwithſtanding his Faith paſſed, give order to his Janizaries to cut all their throats; and, that the execution might be more terrible, to do it in the night, by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102362:17"/>
the light of lanterns and torches. Of all this number there were onely ſeven and twenty eſcaped, who were reſerved by Amurat to be carryed to Conſtantinople to adorn his Triumph.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as this bloody execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ended, the ſacking of the City was given to the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; which continued three days, with all imaginable cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; their avarice not diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Mahometans from Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, nor Friends from Enemies.</p>
               <p>The loſs of Babylon was a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſchief to the Chriſtians than to the Perſian: for as long as this place ſtood, the Ottoman Forces were continually employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon this frontier, and waſted with long marches through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102362:18"/>
and uninhabited Countrys; ſo that they did but now and then moleſt the Chriſtians. But from the loſs of Babylon, and the Peace with Perſia, the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of Chriſtendom may take their date. From hence it is that Poland and Hungary have been of late invaded, and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia loſt. And ſince this time the Perſian hath attempted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing conſiderable; but hanged up his Scymeter againſt the wall, and let his Arms grow ruſty for want of uſe.</p>
               <p>This hazardous enterprize of Babylon being brought to ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a concluſion, Amurat would have purſued this Victory into Perſia, but that he was ſtay'd by ſome indiſpoſition of health; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102362:18"/>
at the ſame time he received a Letter from the Favourite Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana, being then upon the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier attending his return; who invited him from the aſſaults of War, to thoſe of Love. A woman of a moſt charming behaviour, and ſo bountiful, that ſhe gave the Meſſenger who brought her the news of the taking of Babylon ten thouſand Dollars.</p>
               <p>Amurat, who was unbounded in his Rewards as well as Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to requite the Grand Viſir, who was ſlain in the Siege, made his Son, though very young, Governour of Meſopotamia, one of the moſt eſteemed Commands in the Empire: and Muſtapha Baſſa, who had been ſo great an inſtrument in the taking of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102362:19"/>
he advanced to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Viſirſhip. He ſent his chief Ecuyer with a rich Preſent of Sables to the Queen his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to acquaint her with his ſucceſs; having ever born her a moſt filial reverence. To reward this grateful News, the Queen ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of her Son the Baſſaſhip of Bulgaria, and confer'd it upon the Meſſeger.</p>
               <p>Amurat, at his departure from Babylon, left the Grand Viſir behind him, with ſecret inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions not to reject any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble offers of Peace: and then he diſmiſſed the Perſian Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, whom he had kept Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with him all this while; and delivered him a Letter in anſwer to that which the Ambaſſadour
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102362:19"/>
had brought him from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; the tenor of which was: <hi>I who am Lord of Lords, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Arabia, Perſia, and Greece, exalted by the aid of God to the Empire of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Poſſeſſor of the White and Black Sea, Lord of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Houſe of Mecca and Medina, as alſo of Hieruſalem, Aleppo, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus, and of all thoſe Holy and Venerable places, of Cairo and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, of Ethiopia and the leſſer Aſia, of the Georgians and the Tartars, and in a word, ſupreme Lord of the ſeven Climates, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Amurat Can, To the brave Soffi, to whom God give peace if he deſerve it. As ſoon as this my Imperial Letter, which is fit to be obeyed, ſhall come to thee, be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102362:20"/>
it known that the cauſe why I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained till now thy Ambaſſadour whom thou haſt ſent to my happy Port to ſue for Peace, was, that I might ſubdue Bagdat; which I have done, thanks to the edge of my Invincible Sword. If thou deſireſt to be quiet, deliver up thoſe Provinces which were the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of my unconquered Anceſtors, putting them into the hands of my Beglerbegs, who will advance thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my victorious and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible Army. Otherwiſe expect me in the Spring with my Troops, more numerous than the ſands of the Sea, in the bowels of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. That ſhall ſucceed which is determined from eternity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31-61" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102362:20"/>The deſtruction of Camels and beaſts of burden had been ſo great in this march, that there were ſcarce enough remaining to carry home the Baggage to Conſtantinople, whither Amurat was now haſtning, to ſolace him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after his fatigues, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh his Souldiers. The Sultana's and all the Miniſters vied with one another who ſhould get the richeſt Regalo's to preſent their Monarch; which, with thoſe which were ſent him by the Queen-Mother, were in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted at above a Million of Gold.</p>
               <p>Upon the way, his Majeſty was ſeized with ſo violent a Head-ach, that he could not ſtand: whereupon his Phyſicians
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102362:21"/>
were ſent for. The next day he was taken with a trembling, which at firſt was looked upon as the effect of a Fever; but continuing, they apprehended it might turn to a Palſie or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy. With this he had ſo great a ſwelling in his legs, that he could hardly ſit on horſe-back; the ſtate of his health being ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed by his exceſſes of Wine and Women.</p>
               <p>The Sultana Favourite came before him into Conſtantinople with ſix Gallies; and the Queen-Mother, attended by all the Grandees, went out to meet him; and then he made his entry with a number of Coaches cover'd with cloth of Gold. At the end of the Cavalcade Amurat him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102362:21"/>
appeared, dreſſed in a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian habit, with two and twenty Slaves of the chief men of that Nation, whom he had taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners at Babylon. His treaſure carried by ten Gallies was landed at the Seraglio: and that which he brought home, was calculated to be more than what he took out when he began his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Chriſtian Princes grow rich by Peace, but the Turk by War; who repairs his expences out of the Avanies which he lays upon his rich Subjects, and out of the Spoils of the Nations which he conquers.</p>
               <p>Being now returned home, the firſt thing he did was to ſhew that rage which he had ſo long hidden, for the indignity
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102362:22"/>
which was done him in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in ſaving Ibrahim when he had commanded his death. And therefore he gave orders that thoſe Sultana's and all their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who had a hand in that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhould be ſtrangled, leaving the unfortunate Ibrahim alive but till he had a Son born to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Empire.</p>
               <p>And now Amurat elated with his Victories, ſeemed to be above Fortune, and to deſpiſe all things, even his own Law and his own Religion, and to care neither for man nor God. He put his Mufti to death; which the moſt tyrannical of his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had never attempted; laughed at all Devotion, &amp; would not faſt at the Ramaſan: but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102362:22"/>
abandoning himſelf to all kind of diſſolution, one night he made ſo great a debauche, that they were fain to carry him to bed; though but a little before, he had made a Vow, being very ſick, that he would never drink Wine more; and cauſed all the Cups and Glaſſes with which he had made his debauches to be broke, though ſome of them were of Cryſtal of the Rock, and others of Stones of great price. But this laſt debauch put an end to all his extravagancies: for being ſeized upon by an unintermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Fever, his Phyſicians were in that fear, that they durſt not direct any Remedies, leſt if they failed to give him Life, they ſhould procure their own Deaths.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102362:23"/>
But being preſſed by the Queen-Mother and the great Miniſters to do ſomething, they agreed to let him blood: which had an ill effect; for he died preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the flower of his age, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lived thirty three years, and reigned fifteen.</p>
               <p>Amurat being dead, the chief Viſir with all the Grandees of the Court repaired to the Priſon where Ibrahim was kept, the onely ſurviving Prince of the Royal Family. When they came to the door to ſalute him Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, he ſuſpected it an artifice of his Brother to take away his life; and lifting his hands to Heaven, prayed to God to preſerve the King his Brother, for the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and glory of the Ottoman
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102362:23"/>
Empire. But they all confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to him with proteſtations the death of Amurat, and the change of Ibrahims Fortune, which tranſlated him from the Grave to the Throne; after ſome reſiſtance he let them into his Chamber, where they found him almoſt ſtifled with ſtench and putrefaction; the Negro-woman who attended him being dead in the Room, and no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der taken to carry the Corpſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. But ſtill being jealous that the news which they brought him was not true, he declared to the company, that if it were ſo as they told him, that God had taken to himſelf the Emperour his Brother, he would not ſtir out of his Chamber till he had ſeen
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102362:24"/>
his body. They ſeeing him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, to comply with his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure fetched the Corpſe of Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat to the priſon, and lay'd it down before him. At the ſight of which, Ibrahim had that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that he ſeemed to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the very carcaſs; and not truſting to his eyes, would feel with his hands if he were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, who had kept him ſo many years in a kind of perpetual death. Nor yet ſatisfied with feeling the body cold and ſtiff, he kneeled down and put his mouth to the mouth of the Corpſe, to try if he could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it breathe. At laſt, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that great Monarch dead and unmovable, who had held in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo long a great part of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102362:24"/>
world, he roſe up, and ſaid theſe words, becoming the Majeſty of a free Prince: <hi>There lies the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt King and the greateſt Tyrant that ever was.</hi> And then walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, they cloathed him in purple, and proclaimed him Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour with loud acclamations of the Souldiers and the People.</p>
               <p>And ſo he began his Reign auſpiciouſly, and had made his Subjects happy, if he had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued as he began: for he confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Peace with the State of Venice, entred into an allyance with France, and had a fair Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency with all the great Potentates of Europe. And to give the world an opinion of the clemency of his nature, he commanded the Grand Viſir that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102362:25"/>
he ſhould put no man to death but for juſt and urgent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>The Grand Viſir thinking this mildneſs of Ibrahim to proceed from his ſimplicity, began to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern as deſpotically as if he had been Emperour himſelf. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the Court all the great Miniſters and Servants of Amurat, upon pretence of giving them Governments and Charges; and filled the Family of Ibrahim with his own Dependants. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Selectar Baſſa he had not power to diſplace, nor to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy any where elſe, in regard of the nature of his Office, which kept him always about the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Emperour: Yet he prevailed ſo far with his arts and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102362:25"/>
cunning, that he at laſt got his head, and ſo remained Arbiter of all affairs.</p>
               <p>During theſe changes in the Court, as Ibrahim one day was enjoying the pleaſure of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, which till then he had not of a long time ſeen but out of a grate, one of the old Gardners of the Seraglio came and caſt himſelf at his feet: which he perceiving, ſtay'd to ſpeak with him, asking him what news there was in the Court, and what the World ſaid of his perſon. The Gardner taking hold of the occaſion, had the courage to tell him, that all good men were troubled to ſee his Majeſty more a ſlave to his own ſlave, than he had lately been to the King his Brother.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102362:26"/>
Ibrahim wondring at what he ſaid, asked him who it was that he was a ſlave to? <hi>To the Grand Viſir,</hi> replied the Gardner. <hi>See, Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>if in all thy Court there be the face of any Miniſter or Servant of the Emperour Amurat. No,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>there is not one: All of them are baniſhed by Muſtapha; onely the Selectar, who by reaſon of his Office could not be taken from thy perſon, hath loſt his head, becauſe he would not be an Inſtrument of his Tyranny. Look about thee, and thou wilt ſee thy ſelf ſurrounded with his Dependants and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; nor canſt thou move one of thy eyes but he knows it. Thou art here ſhut up and loſt amongst Women, whilſt thy Viſir commands all the Men of thy Empire. Awake,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102362:26"/>
and think of thy Brother Amurat, who though for reaſons of State he kept thee a Priſoner, was a great and wiſe Prince, and would not let his Slaves be his Maſters. He loved his Subjects, and protected them from the oppreſſion of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Souldiers. He would know every thing; and as he was the chief man in his Empire for his quality and merit, he would be the chief in adminiſtring juſtice, and concerning himſelf for the ſafety of his people. Make thy ſelf a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Succeſſor of ſo great a Prince, who having with his arms ſubdued half the World, hath founded this mighty Empire upon the baſis of Honour and Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The words of this old man made an incredible impreſſion in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102362:27"/>
the breaſt of Ibrahim, who being ſenſible that that was too true which the Gardner told him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to free himſelf from the ſubjection he was in, and do ſome ſurprizing thing, that the world might ſee he was maſter of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and knew how to command without the help of others. The Office of Selectar was now va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant by the arts of the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir, who had taken off the head of him who laſt poſſeſſed it; nor was it known upon whom For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune would confer this important Charge, to which all the youth of the Seraglio aſpired, as to the higheſt reward of Vertue. Nor did the Grand Viſir care for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any Selectar at all, leſt it ſhould diminiſh his authority, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102362:27"/>
make one of thoſe who were now at his command, his compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titor in the Government. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Ibrahim reſolved to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the election of this Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, and commanded there ſhould a great Feaſt be made, ſuch as is uſual at the creation of the Selectar.</p>
               <p>Upon the news of this, the Grand Viſir was infinitely trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; not ſo much for the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of having a Rival in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours favour, as for finding in Ibrahim a Genius to command, and an aſſurance in doing buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that concernment without participating it to him. So that he durſt not directly oppoſe the Grand Seigniors reſolution, which would have been a capital of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102362:28"/>
but artificially endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to diſcredit the election, by telling him that his Highneſs needed not take care to make a Feaſt for the exaltation of one of his ſlaves, ſince Feaſts were moſt proper for the Triumphs of Princes. Ibrahim heard him with much coldneſs, telling him that he would advance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs whom he pleaſed; and for all his remonſtrances, would ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate a Feaſt for the Creation of the Selectar, according to the cuſtom of his Progenitors. Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha was ſilent, as if he had been ſtruck with thunder; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at ſo ſudden a change in the Sultan, found that he was miſtaken in thinking Ibrahim an Idiot; and that that dulneſs and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102362:28"/>
ſtolidity which had appeared in him, was rather an effect of his long impriſonment, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual apprehenſion he had been in of death, than want of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts and underſtanding.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Grand Viſir was gone, Ibrahim commanded that they ſhould look him out a poor Gardner called Iſuf Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couich, and conduct him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to his preſence. Iſuf underſtanding he was ſent for by the Grand Seignior, imagined that his laſt hour was come, and that he was fetch'd to be put to death for diſcovering the late Emperour Amurat, and betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſecrets to Ibrahim, who might reaſonably think he would do the like by him; ſince Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102362:29"/>
though they make uſe of Traytors, do always hate them. But he was quickly undeceived: for Ibrahim came out to meet him, and imbracing him with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen arms, and kiſſing him, told the company that this was he whom he would make Selectar Baſſa; and that he thought it juſtice and gratitude to do it, ſince Iſuf was the onely perſon in the world who had obliged him, having with the utmoſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of his life ſerved him in his calamity, when none alive but he durſt own him. An heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal piece of Gratitude, and fit to be recorded to ſucceeding Ages! If Ibrahim had not ſtained the luſtre of this action by other o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and deteſtable vices, he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102362:29"/>
had not gone out of the world as he did, with the opinion of a Monſter and a mad-man, but been eternized by Fame amongſt the moſt vertuous Princes.</p>
               <p>Iſuf, who but the day before had nothing in the world that he could call his own, being now created Selectar, found himſelf in an inſtant, with what his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter gave him, and with the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents which were made him by the Sultana's and the Grandees of the Court, worth a million of Gold. Some ſending him Jewels, others Money, ſome Horſes, others Slaves, others Furniture for his houſe. And that he might be as great as For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune could make a Subject, Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him declared him Baſſa of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102362:30"/>
Sea, and gave him to Wife a Lady of the Ottoman houſe.</p>
               <p>But in all this greatneſs and proſperity, he was quickly weary of the Court: for finding that Ibrahim's nature was ſo corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Fortune, that of a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince he was like to make a cruel Tyrant, being bloody, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and uncapable of counſel; he reſolved ſecretly with himſelf to retire from the Court, to a private life, and to paſs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his days in quiet in his own Country. And becauſe this could not be done by a man in his Poſt, without giving ſome ſuſpition, he bethought himſelf of this pretence. It is a cuſtom in Turky for men who are arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to great riches, that they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102362:30"/>
may leſſen Envy, to employ part of them in pious works. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none can found Moſchees but the Grand Seignior himſelf, or ſuch Baſſa's as have conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Provinces or Kingdoms to the Ottoman Empire, he reſolved to build and endow ſome houſes in the Country as Innes for Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, that Travellers might be entertained there in their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys without expence; a thing of great convenience for ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, in that deſert and depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Empire. Communicating then to Sinan Bey his firſt Maſter his deſign of building an Inne for Pilgrims in his own Country, and in the Territory of Urana where he was born, he aſſigned Sinan money to begin the work,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102362:31"/>
and ſent down by him ſeveral Preſents to his kindred, and five hundred Royals to the good old woman who had given him a pair of ſhooes when ſhe met him barefoot on the way.</p>
               <p>Now there ariſing ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute betwixt Sinan Bey and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Agents of Iſuf concerning the covering of this new houſe, one thinking beſt to ſend into Hungary, others into Apulia for Tyles; he ſent to them to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten the work, bidding them not to trouble themſelves about the covering, ſince he would be there time enough himſelf to give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in it. The preparations for this building, and theſe words of Iſuf, that he would be there him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, coming to the knowledge
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102362:31"/>
of the Venetian Miniſters at Conſtantinople, who watch with continual jealouſie every thing that is done and ſaid in that Court, made them ſuſpect that there was ſome miſchief brewing againſt the Republick. For they could not imagine that ſo great a man as the Selectar Baſſa, chief favourite of the Grand Seignior, and one who was thought to bear particular ill-will to the State of Venice, ſhould leave the Court, and come down into Dalmatia, onely to give orders about a building. And therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding that this was but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to cover ſome great deſign, they found a way by Preſents to the Grand Viſir, and other means, in which above all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102362:32"/>
there the Venetians are skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to ſtop the Selectar's Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
               <p>It may eaſily be conceived what a diſappointment this muſt be to the Selectar, who had ſet his heart upon retiring from the Court, that he might put his life and fortunes in ſafety; for the accompliſhing of which, he could deviſe no other means but this. He could not but be troubled too, to be defeated of the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction he had promiſed himſelf in ſeeing his native Country, and ſhewing his Wealth and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs there, where not many years before he had been a miſerable Peaſant. Indeed this ſo increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the averſion he had to the Venetians, that it was not long
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102362:32"/>
before they felt moſt heavy ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his reſentment. Of ſo much moment ſometimes, in the greateſt affairs of State, are little diſguſts given to the Miniſters of Princes.</p>
               <p>About this time Ibrahim was meditating a War againſt Malta, in revenge of an injury which he had received from the Malteſe upon this occaſion: The Grand Sultana amongſt her At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants had a Georgian Lady, a moſt gentile and charming beauty, with whom Ibrahim took his pleaſure, and had a Son by her. This ſo diſturbed the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana who govern'd his affections, to ſee her ſelf Rivalled by her own woman, who daily grew in the favour of the Sultan, that ſhe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102362:33"/>
cauſed a ſlow poyſon to be given her, which deſtroyed her health, and preyed upon her beauty; and had certainly carried her to her grave, but that Antidotes, joyned with youth and a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſtitution, overcame it. However, the Georgian thought her ſelf unſafe in the Court, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an implacable enemy of the Sultana; ſo that one day ſhe caſt her ſelf at Ibrahims feet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him to give her leave to perform a Vow ſhe had made to their great Prophet; which was, to go in pilgrimage to Mec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, to carry her little Son there to be circumciſed. But Ibrahim was ſo fond of her, that he would not hear of it, till ſhe told him that it was not onely the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102362:33"/>
ſatisfaction of her Conſcience, but the conſideration of her Health, that obliged her to make this humble ſute to him; ſince her Phyſicians had aſſured her ſhe was in danger of death by her ill habit of body, and that they knew nothing ſo likely to reſtore her as the Bathes of Rhodes, which were in her way to Mecca. This made Ibrahim at laſt, though with much relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy, conſent to her Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. But he had that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for her, that he ordered the beſt ſhip he had to carry her; and appointed Gelis Aga, one of the greateſt Aga's of the Court, who had been a Favourite to three Grand Seigniors, to attend and take care of her. And ſo
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102362:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in September 1644, this Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian Lady with her little Son im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued for Rhodes, with forty Women and thirty Pages, and all other equipage ſutable to the condition of a perſon who had the favour of ſo great a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. They had not been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days at Sea, when ſix Galleys of Malta, who were cruzing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Iſle of Rhodes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcried about break of day a great Gallion bearing Turkiſh Colours; and making up to her, began a bloody fight, which continued many hours; wherein Boisbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant General of the Galleys was ſlain, and ſeveral other Knights of Malta, with one hundred and ſixteen Officers, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty ſix wounded. At
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102362:34"/>
laſt the old Aga being kill'd, they boarded the Gallion, taking the Lady with her Son and her retinue, and three hundred and fourſcore other Turks, beſides two rich Merchant-ſhips which were in company. The Gallion was ſo torn with the ſhot receiv'd in the fight, that ſhe founder'd in the Sea before they could get to Malta. And the Lady op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt with grief for her misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and the captivity of her Son, dyed in a little time after her arrival there. The Great Maſter gave the young child to the Dominican Fryars to breed him up in the Chriſtian Religion; which they did with that ſucceſs, that when he came to years of underſtanding, he did not onely
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102362:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
make profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith, but entered into a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life, and took upon him the habit of a Dominican, and the name of Father Dominique Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman. In this Habit I ſaw him at Paris in the Court of the Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobins, in the year 1665, being carryed thither by the Venetian Ambaſſadour Seignior Alviſi Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredo, now Patriarch of Venice, to whom he gave a picture of himſelf, which I now have. The Dominicans had taught him ſo well, that he had the knowledge of moſt Sciences, and ſpoke five or ſix Languages. And though he ſeemed under the habit of a Fryar to have the meen of a Prince, he conform'd himſelf ſtrictly to the Rules of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102362:35"/>
nor could I ſee any diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betwixt him and others of the Convent, but that he left the Ambaſſadour at the ſtair foot, whilſt the other Fathers atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to his Coach.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61-90" type="pages">
               <p>Ibrahim hearing of the loſs of his Ship and the captivity of his Miſtriſs, fell into ſuch a rage, that no man durſt ſpeak to him; vowing he would be revenged in the extirpation of the Malteſe. And then commanded his Army to be drawn together, and a Fleet to be made ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege Malta. But his great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Councellors, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the difficulty of this enterprize, took a time to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him from it; repreſenting to him that the voyage was very
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102362:36"/>
long, the ſeaſon of the year ſpent, and that he had not Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ready to man ſo great a Fleet as was neceſſary for ſuch an Expedition; and above all, they minded him of the ſtrength of the place which he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege, which was not onely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably fortified both by Art and Nature, but defended by the moſt expert men of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who having no imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but to fight, were bred Souldiers from their infancy, and with a few Galleys kept the whole Levant in awe.</p>
               <p>Upon which, Ibrahim, who would not be contradicted, as knowing no reaſon but his own will, grew into that fury, that he had like to have put them to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102362:36"/>
death who made this remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance to him; ſo that for ſome time no man durſt open his mouth to him any more upon this matter. At laſt, one of the Viſirs who had more courage than the reſt, ſaid, <hi>None of us know what Malta is, having ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been there; but it would be fit, before your Highneſs reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo great an enterprize, that you had exact information from ſome one who hath been upon the place;</hi> and then told him that he knew an Aga lately come from thence, who had been a ſlave there four years, and could give a perfect account of all things, if it were his pleaſure to command him. Upon which the Aga being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Ibrahim bad him faithfully
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102362:37"/>
and freely relate to him the ſtate of that Iſland. The Aga with profound obeiſance aſſured him that the ſtrength of Malta was conſiderable; that beſides the advantage of the ſcituation and double fortifications, which made it almoſt impregnable, it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by men of high reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that all the Campagne round the Town was nothing but a hard rock, without earth to work on, ſo that it was almoſt impoſſible to make any Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; that the Fleet which ſhould bring an Army there, could not ſtay before the place, by reaſon of want of Ports, and the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious winds which reigned in thoſe Chanels; that Italy and Sicily were ſo near, that the place
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102362:37"/>
would continually receive ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours; and laſt of all, that Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta was ſo far from Conſtantinople, that his Army could not arrive there time enough; it being neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for whoever would beſiege that place, to be there in June, ſince in three months time they of neceſſity muſt retire, the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts in thoſe Seas were ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent about the beginning of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptember.</p>
               <p>Theſe reaſons, ſo contrary to the deſigns of Ibrahim, inſtead of ſatisfying him, did but inflame his anger. But however, that he might know all that the Aga could tell him, he asked him what People thoſe Malteſe were, who made the Conqueſt of Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſo difficult. The Aga anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102362:38"/>
that they were a body of Nobility drawn from all parts of Chriſtendom; and naming the Knights Nation by Nation, told him that the major part of them were Frenchmen; that their Prince the great Maſter who commanded them was a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and that to make the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize eaſie, it would be beſt for his Highneſs to try if he could prevail with the King of France to call home the Knights of that Nation; without which it would be almoſt impoſſible to take Malta.</p>
               <p>At theſe words Ibrahim was ſo incenſed, that he ſtorm'd as if he had been mad; and hardly knowing what he ſaid or did, commanded them immediately to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:102362:38"/>
bring him the French Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour's head: which had certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been done, but that the Chiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Aga, a black Eunuch who was there, diverted him. This Aga being a grave man, and of great reputation for his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well as Zeal for the Grand Seigniors Service, remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to him, how that for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove theſe threeſcore years, in which he had had the honour to ſerve five Emperours, he had ſeen many Wars, and great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities had befallen the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; but in all the Conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his time, he had never known ſo much as mention made of cutting off an Ambaſſadours head: that ſuch an indignity could not be done to ſo potent a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102362:39"/>
Monarch as the King of France, but it would be revenged; and if the Galleys of Malta could give his Highneſs ſuch diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, what might the King of France do with the mighty For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Kingdom? That this action was contrary to all Reaſon of State and good Government, and would redound much to the prejudice of his Empire, which his Anceſtors had maintained from time to time as well by prudence as by power.</p>
               <p>This diſcourſe was heard with applauſe by all the Council: but Ibrahim, who meaſured the reaſon of all things by his own caprice, was ſo offended with him who made it, that in a rage he commanded the unfortunate Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102362:39"/>
to be put to death. The Council, though they were ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the danger to which they expoſed themſelves, were ſo tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the injuſtice of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and had that reſpect for the Chizlar Aga, that they interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for him. But all they could obtain, was to have the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Death changed into Exile. And ſo the poor man was baniſhed to Gallipoli, and in an inſtant deſpoiled of all which he had been getting in the ſervice of threeſcore years.</p>
               <p>The enterprize of Malta be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found not adviſable, and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahim ſtill breathing hate and revenge againſt the Chriſtians, propoſed in Council to fall upon Sicily; which if they were once
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102362:40"/>
Maſters of, Malta could not long reſiſt, ſince from thence it had all its proviſions. Some Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilian Bandito's, who commonly are the moſt mortal enemies of their own Country, had ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted this to the Grand Viſir, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him that they would put Syracuſa into his hand; which he being once poſſeſſed of, might with little difficulty ſubdue the reſt of that Kingdom. Others ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd an expedition into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Naples. But both theſe Propoſitions being rejected, they fell into diſcourſe of Candia; when Iſuf Selectar Baſſa, to whom Fortune now preſented an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be revenged of the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, repreſented to them, that in his opinion that buſineſs was the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102362:40"/>
moſt feaſible of any thing that had yet been thought of: And that it was juſt too, ſince the Malteſe, who took the Grand Seigniors Gallion, after this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit landed firſt in Candia, and were courteouſly received there by the Inhabitants, who bought their Prizes of them.</p>
               <p>But for the preſent, this was ſecretly diverted by the Grand Viſir, who was a friend to the Republick of Venice; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Mufti as contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their Law, which will not allow a War to be made againſt Chriſtians when they are in War amongſt themſelves, for fear they ſhould unite together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Believers. Beſides, the Mufti ſaid that it would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:102362:41"/>
to invade any Prince before they had declared War againſt him. Upon which, there was nothing at that time concluded. But Ibrahim in his own mind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined now to turn his Arms upon Candia; which was a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret he would depoſit no-where but in the boſom of the Selectar; and therefore kept it from the knowledge even of the Grand Viſir, for fear he ſhould diſcover his deſign to the Venetians, with whom he ſuſpected that he kept intelligence.</p>
               <p>In a few days after this, the Ambaſſadours of France and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice were ſent for to Court, and given to underſtand that the Grand Seignior deſired to know of them who theſe people were
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102362:41"/>
who had taken his Gallion; and why they the Ambaſſadours had not adviſed him of it without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked. To ſo impertinent a queſtion their anſwer was, that they knew nothing of it, and that it was certain it was come to paſs without the conſent of their Princes, who deſired to maintain a ſincere correſpondence with the Grand Seignior. It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that his Highneſs was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed to underſtand that the King of France his ancient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate ſhould ſend his Subjects to Malta to make war upon him under the Banners of others; that he had always held the King of France for his very good Friend, but that for the future he ſhould look upon him as his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102362:42"/>
mortal Enemy, if he did not call his Knights of Malta home, and make them reſtore all that they had taken upon his Gallion. To this the French Ambaſſadour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that the French who liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Malta were out of the Kingdom of France; that the King his Maſter had no authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over them, that Iſland being tributary to the King of Spain, who was then in war with France; and as for the reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goods which were taken by men who did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon his King, there was no reaſon why they ſhould ſpeak to him of it.</p>
               <p>Then they began to reproach the Venetian Ambaſſadour, that the Miniſters of the Republick,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102362:42"/>
contrary to the Peace ſworn with the Grand Seignior, had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven free ingreſs to the Malta Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys into the Ports of Candia; and that after the taking of his Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, they had there landed men and horſes, and ſold their Prizes: And therefore to prevent the like inconvenience for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, his Highneſs demanded of them the Port of Suda, to ſecure his Fleet which he was ſending to beſiege Malta. The Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour anſwered, That Candia had never entertained the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys of Malta: That the Grand Seignior was miſinformed, and that he would acquaint the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with his demand; but that he did verily believe they would never grant it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:102362:43"/>In the mighty preparations which were now making for the invaſion of Candia, Ibrahim and the Selectar with moſt profound diſſimulation endeavour'd to hide the deſign; and to take all um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage from the Venetians of a War with them, they gave leave for two Drugger-men and a Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizary to paſs to Venice with a Safe-conduct to fetch Seignior Dolfino, who was deſigned Bailo to Conſtantinople, as they were uſed to do in times of peace. And with Seignior Soranzo the preſent Bailo at Conſtantinople they continued all demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of courteſie and friendſhip, to make him believe that Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him intended a ſincere Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with the Republick.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102362:43"/>
But Soranzo, who was a man of an acute and penetrating under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, diſcerned that all this was counterfeit; and that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this appearance of good-will, they were preparing to ſheath their ſwords in the bowels of the Venetians. But not being able to penetrate the certainty of their deſign, he ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited the Senate to provide for Candia. With this concurred the advice of Antonio Nava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giero Proveditor of Canea, who had information from ſome Spies of his at Conſtantinople, that the preparations making were not for Malta. And at the ſame time Navagiero took ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed like Fiſher-men ſounding the depth of the Water about
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102362:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Canea, whom he kept Priſoners, and acquainted the Senate with it; taking occaſion from thence to give them an account of the condition of the place, and what Souldiers and Proviſions were neceſſary for the defence of it. Ragozzi likewiſe, Prince of Tranſylvania, who had conſtant intelligence from Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, adviſed Cardinal Mazarine that the Turk had a deſign upon Candia: which the Cardinal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently imparted to Seignior Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſta Naris the Venetian Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour at Paris. But the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this came not to Venice till after the Venetian Bailo was arreſted, and that the Turkiſh Fleet was under ſail for Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:102362:44"/>The Senate of Venice being now alarmed, and fluctuating in their opinions what to do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the fear of neglecting their own defence on the one ſide, and of provoking the Ottoman power on the other, reſolved on a middle way; which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proves fatal to thoſe who uſe it. And therefore they would not ſend ſuch a force to Candia as might make the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior think they deſigned a War with him, but onely as much as was neceſſary to reinforce their Gariſons, and ſo be onely upon the defenſive, without giving oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of coming to a rupture. So they fitted up two Galleazze, and elected thirty Gentlemen to command ſo many Galleys; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102362:45"/>
order to Cornaro General of Candia to make ready the twenty Galleys of that Kingdom, and to keep them there to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Port of Suda. They likewiſe laded two ſhips with Ammunition and Victuals, which, as they were going for Candia, at the Cape of Mattopan were met with five Veſſels of Biſerta, which engaged them in a bloody fight that continued ſix hours. But at laſt the Venetians, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diſadvantage of their number, opened their way with their Cannon, and came well to Candia. But Capello, who was ſent with other ſhips which carried nine Companies of Foot, with divers Gunners and Enginiers, beſides proviſions of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102362:45"/>
Victual and Powder, arrived at Suda without any ill encounter. Upon which General Cornaro ſent the twenty Galleys of the Kingdom thither, with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Veſſels, for the preſervation of a place upon which it was thought the fate of Candia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended. But experience hath ſhewed what a miſtake that was, and that the preſerving not of Suda, but of Canea, had been the ſaving of that Kingdom. For Canea being taken, which was upon the firm land of the Iſland, there was no force there ſufficient to reſiſt the impreſſions of the Turks; ſo that to looſe that, was to looſe all. Whereas the Fort of Suda was not of that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, being onely a Rock in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102362:46"/>
the Sea, and at a good diſtance from the main land of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as Ibrahim underſtood that his Fleet was ready, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Iſuf Selectar Baſſa Captain-General of the Expedition, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him a Commiſſion ſealed up, with expreſs command not to open it till he came to Nava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rino in the Morea; where he was to conſult with his Captains what courſe to take for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter executing of his deſign. And then he went in perſon to ſee his Armada, where Iſuf caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at his feet, with threeſcore and ten of his chief Officers. It is reported, that Ibrahim being told how the Aga of the Janiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries had ſaid, that if the Army
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102362:46"/>
went for Candia, the Laurels which they brought thence would be watered with Turkiſh blood; cryed out, that they would meet with no oppoſition, and that he had ſent Iſuf to take poſſeſſion for him of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. When Iſuf took his leave, Ibrahim preſented him with a rich Scymitar ſet with Diamonds; and prayed to Mahomet to give him a proſperous and ſucceſsful voyage.</p>
               <p>The Venetian Bailo at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, who began now to get ſome light of the deſign, went, according to the cuſtom of that Court, to compliment the Captain-General at his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; who received him with unuſual courteſie. And the Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102362:47"/>
with a diſſimulation as deep as his, with his tongue wiſhed him a happy Voyage, when in his heart he would have been glad that he and all his Army had been in the bottom of the Sea.</p>
               <p>This great Fleet ſailing out of the Helleſpont, filled all the Kingdoms of the Mediterranean with fear and terrour, none yet knowing where the tempeſt would fall. But it is very ſtrange that the Mufti before they went ſhould declare in the Divan, that this War againſt the Chriſtians was unjuſt, and againſt the Laws of Mahomet. And when they told him that all things were lawful to the Grand Seignior, becauſe he could do whatever
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102362:47"/>
he pleaſed, and none could call him to account for it; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that the Ottoman Force was very great of it ſelf, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal to all Chriſtendom united together; and therefore it was raſhneſs at this time to provoke the Chriſtian Princes, who it was to be feared might now make a greater league together than they had done in the War of Cyprus. The Grand Viſir re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primanded the Mufti for this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, telling him that he was more zealous for his Law, than well acquainted with Reaſon of State, the maximes of which have nothing to do with thoſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>Ibrahim hearing what had paſſed in the Divan, and of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102362:48"/>
Remonſtrances the Mufti had made there, depoſed him from his dignity, to the great ſcandal of the People, who murmured loudly at this action; and ſaid, that God would never bleſs the Ottoman Houſe, as long as the chief Miniſter of his great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet was thus uſed: ſo well-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected are thoſe people, though ignorant and unbelievers, to what they conceive to be according to Law and Juſtice.</p>
               <p>The Selectar now being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſail with his vaſt Fleet, arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at Scio, the moſt delicious Iſland of the Archipelago, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all his Veſſels to take in Water. Here he landed; and after publick Prayers made in a Moſchee for the ſucceſs of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102362:48"/>
his enterprize, he took a review of all his Forces, animating his Souldiers, and filling their minds with great expectations. And being curious to know the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of his general Officers and chief Captains concerning the War he was going to make, he called a Council; and concealing the Orders he had from the Grand Seignior to invade Candia, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them onely a Commiſſion which he had received to make War upon the Chriſtians; and ſo deſired their advice where to begin the War moſt for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and glory of the Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire. Aſſan Baſſa, an Albaneſe of great reputation in the Army, began a diſcourſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the attacking of Malta; and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102362:49"/>
when he had ſet forth the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardouſneſs of that enterprize, and the diſaſtrous ſucceſs of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly attempting that place; he concluded, that he did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it. Amurat Aga of the Janizaries concur'd with him, adding, that there was no going to beſiege any place in the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Seas, without good har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to retire to: intimating thereby, that to fall upon Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia would be more commodious. All the other Captains ſeemed to be of the ſame opinion. But the General of Barbary could not contain himſelf from falling ſoul upon the Venetians, remembring the defeat which the Barbary Galleys had received at the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona, and not conſidering the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:102362:49"/>
vaſt ſum which the Republick had given to make up that breach. And to exaſperate the Council, he at laſt aſſured them that the onely remedy they had to repair paſt injuries, and to prevent fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, was to deſpoil the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of Candia, which was the Sanctuary of the Chriſtian Pirats; and that this was very eaſie at this time to be effected, ſince the Inhabitants were deſperately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, and the Iſland unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of all things neceſſary for a defence.</p>
               <p>The Selectar was much pleas'd to find the opinion of his Officers ſo well quadrate with his deſign; and preſenting them with Herns feathers for their Turbants, as a mark of his eſteem, he ſet ſail for
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:102362:50"/>
Negropont. As he paſſed by Tine, the laſt Iſland of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick in the Archipelago, to make the Venetians more ſecure, he ſent a Frigat and two Saichs into the Harbour, to demand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to take water there; giving out that the Fleet was bound for Malta. Staying here ſome days, and having received all ſorts of refreſhments from Seignior Riva Proveditor of the Iſland, he came to Cape Colonna, from whence he diſpatched away a Frigat to Ibrahim, to give him an account of his Voyage, and of the Courteſies he had received from the Venetians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="90-120" type="pages">
               <p>The cruel Prince ſeeing he could no longer hide his deſign for Candia, on a ſudden own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:102362:50"/>
his treachery, and ſaid, that the reaſon why he had ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, was to ſecure his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; and that he had but broken faith with thoſe, who had firſt broke it with him. And then he commanded to ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Venetian Bailo in his own houſe, and to put a guard of Souldiers upon him: excuſing this horrid violation of the Law of Nations to the Ambaſſadours of other Princes, by ſaying, he did this to prevent the Bailo from diſcovering his deſigns to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as it was known at Venice that their Bailo at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople was arreſted, and a War begun, they ſent to the great Potentates of Chriſtendom
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102362:51"/>
to ſollicit ſuccour. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour excuſed himſelf upon his inability to help them, ſince he had occaſion for his Troops him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. England was engaged in a miſerable civil War, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be expected thence. Holland would not meddle, out of conſideration of the trade they had in Turky; nor ſhew them any further favour, than to ſell them ſhips for their money; a Courteſie which they would not have denied their Enemies. But the Queen of France, for the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of her Regency, gave them four Fire-ſhips, and a hundred thouſand Crowns in money, with permiſſion to raiſe what Officers and Souldiers they could in France. The Spaniard, who
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:102362:51"/>
was nearer the danger by reaſon of his Kingdoms of Sicily and Naples, made magnificent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but furniſhed out onely five Galleys. The Pope ſet out five more, and publiſhed a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, giving leave to the State of Venice to raiſe a hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns in gold upon their own Clergy. The Grand Duke ſent two Companies of Germans, which he drew out of his Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and five Galleys; which, with the Pope's and the Spaniſh Galleys, and ſix Galleys of Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, made one and twenty Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys; and were commanded as a diſtinct Fleet by Prince Lodovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio, as General of the Church. The Duke of Parma ſent two thouſand men; and the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noueſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:102362:52"/>
made mighty offers, but upon ſuch conditions as were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. For they required to be treated with the ſame reſpect as the State of Venice, and to have their Arms ſet up in the Vatican-Hall at Rome, as the Venetians have, amongſt the crowned heads: a demand, which the State of Venice choſe rather to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Succours than conſent to.</p>
               <p>At this time the miſeries of Candia were foretold by ſeveral ſtrange Preſages, as great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, and births of Monſters; and, which was moſt of all taken notice of, the front of St Mark's Church, and part of one of the Baſtions called St. Mark, fell down to the ground of their own accord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:102362:52"/>The fame of the Ottoman Fleet in the Archipelago being come to Candia, and of their watring at Tine with ſo much civility, as likewiſe of ſeveral Turkiſh ſhips having been enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and regaled at Cerigo by the Rector of that Iſland, to whom they brought reſpectful Letters from Coroaga Baſſa of Rhodes, made the people hope that the apprehenſions they had conceived were without ground, and that the Ottoman Fleet was deſigned for ſome other place than Candia: Fortune does ſo delight to delude Mortals with ſome momentary quiet, that the calamities which are to come may fall more heavy upon them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:102362:53"/>Of all the Iſlands of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterranean, Candia is one of the moſt famous, and moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. No place hath afforded more matter for the invention of ancient Poets, who made it the Country of the Gods, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom where Saturn reigned, and where Jupiter was born. It lies at the entrance of the Archipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lago, in almoſt an equal diſtance from Europe, Africa, and Aſia. The form of it is long and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, being near two hundred and fifty miles in length, and not fifty in breadth; and the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence about ſix hundred miles. For fertility of ſoil, few Countrys in the world exceed it; and though it do not abound in Corn ſo much as ſome other
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102362:53"/>
places, it makes up that in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, Oyls, and generous Wines, in which it hath hardly any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual. By reaſon of the narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the valleys, it hath no navigable Rivers; but is full of excellent Springs and Fountains, Caverns and Grotto's, where the Inhabitants repair in the furious heats of Summer, to refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The hundred Cities for which it was ſo much celebrated by the Antients, at this day ſeems a Fable, ſince there are now but four in being, viz. Candia, Sitia, Rhetimo, and Canea.</p>
               <p>At the time of the Invaſion it had about two hundred thouſand Souls, twenty Galleys, a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable body of Horſe maintained by thoſe whom they call Feuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:102362:54"/>
and who poſſeſs the Lands of the Country; and a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia of Foot in the nature of Trainbands. It hath two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Havens: Spina longa to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt of the Iſland, and towards the Weſt Suda, both of them defended with good Forts ſcituated in Iſlands. So that till now it was thought ſo ſtrong, that the Turks had never the courage to aſſault it; nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably had they done it now, if ſome of the Inhabitants, Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to God and their Prince, had not invited and opened them a way to it. It was firſt governed by Kings, then an Ariſtocracy, after that made a Colony by the Romans; then it came to the Greek Emperours; and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:102362:54"/>
laſt of all, upon the taking of Conſtantinople by the Latines, and the dividing of the Empire betwixt the French and the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, it came both by purchaſe and right of Conqueſt to the Venetians, under whoſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions it continued till it was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken by the Turks.</p>
               <p>As the Candiots were comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves with the thoughts of the danger they had eſcaped, believing the Turks gone for Malta; upon a ſudden, by fires from the hills where they kept Watch, they underſtood with horrour and amazement that the Fleet ſtood in for Candia. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagiero Proveditor of Canea immediately ſent away divers of the City to raiſe the Country,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:102362:55"/>
and warned in the Gentlemen Feudataries of that part of the Kingdom, conjuring them to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite themſelves for the common defence: but there was not much fruit of that Meſſage, ſince moſt of the Gentlemen were Bandited, and gone from home in contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy to the Laws. But many of the Country-men came run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Canea, demanding Arms and Ammunition, and ſhewing great forwardneſs to oppoſe the landing of the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The next morning, being the thirteenth of June, in the year 1645, the Turkiſh Fleet appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red off of Cabo Spada; and ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with a gentle gale with their Galleys in the Vant-guard, came to an Anchor over againſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102362:55"/>
a place called the Gogna, where they rode about two miles from ſhore. After they had refreſhed themſelves ſome hours, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached land, and imbarquing their men in little boats, landed them without the leaſt oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For ſuch was the baſe cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardiſe of the Country-people who were drawn up in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to defend the ſhore, that at the very firſt ſight of the Turkiſh Veſſels they abandoned their Poſt, and ran away to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; chooſing rather to meet death or ſlavery in an ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious flight, than by bravely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding their lives endeavour to ſave their Country.</p>
               <p>The Forces which were lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded marched with flying Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:102362:56"/>
towards Canea, whilſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of them preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before San Teodoro, where there were two Forts; the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of which had been lately vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited by the General of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and diſmantled as unuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. In the lower there were onely forty ſouldiers in gariſon, which were newly reinforced with twenty five more, upon the firſt advice of the Turks ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching. It was an eaſie thing for ſuch a Force, after a battery of many hours, to take this place by aſſault; and yet it coſt the Turks very dear. For the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain who was in the Fort valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his liberty above his life, as the Turks were entered gave fire to a Mine, and blew himſelf
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102362:56"/>
with his wife and children into the air, with above two thouſand of his Enemies. The name of this Captain, whoſe memory cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly deſerves to live, was Biagio Giuliani, a Subject of the State of Venice, and native of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Capo D'Iſtria.</p>
               <p>San Teodoro being taken, the Turks brought moſt of their Fleet into that Port, and there continued diſimbarking till they had landed the reſt of their men, with their Machines, Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Artillery; in doing of which they had no diſturbance either from Land or Sea. The Fleet conſiſted of fourſcore Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, two Galeons, two hundred Saichs and Caramuſſals, with a vaſt number of Barks and other
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:102362:57"/>
Veſſels. They landed, as the Turks themſelves reported, ſixty thouſand fighting men. With theſe were many French and Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Enginiers and Gunners, Smiths, Carpenters, and other Artificers; and a ſtately Train of great and ſmall Artillery, with abundance of all other warlike proviſion. Two days after their landing, appeared a Tartan and two Saichs, with ten Frigats of Barbary; which were eſteemed the beſt Veſſels of all the Fleet.</p>
               <p>At this time Antonio Nava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giero was Proveditor of Canea, and Count Dominico Albano of Bergamo Governour. In the place, beſides the Townſmen, were fourteen Companies of Foot, which made a body of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:102362:57"/>
eight hundred men effective. There was a Troop of Stradiots alſo in the Town, which was all their Horſe; and of the Country-Volonteers, not above one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men. Of the Militia of the Country, five hundred thirty five Souldiers; which, with a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thirty two Scholars of the Town, were then all the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants. Navagiero wrote to the ſeveral diviſions of the Countrey with all ſpeed to ſend their men into Canea: but their Leaders could not perſwade them to come; only from Bicorno appear'd five hundred men; but as ſoon as they came in ſight of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Camp, they fled; and, for all the diligence the Officers could uſe, they could not get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:102362:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a hundred of them ſtay. Upon the firſt alarm of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Turkiſh Army, there came many women with their children running out of the Country into the Town: Upon which the Proveditor thought to chooſe ſome of the moſt ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of them, and to turn out the reſt: but the Citizens ſeeming diſcontented at it, he conſented they ſhould ſtay; and it proved to good purpoſe, ſince he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards made great uſe of them in the Siege. Theſe were all the Forces which were in Canea when the Turks landed: But before they began to attack it, there got in three hundred more of the Country-Militia, &amp; a Band of a hundred Caloieres, which
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:102362:58"/>
are a ſort of Greek Fryars or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men of the Order of St. Baſil; who did excellent ſervice, and were as forward to expoſe themſelves as any of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, in all the moſt deſperate exigencies of the Siege.</p>
               <p>Though Canea had the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a ſtrong Town of War, it was not ſo indeed: For the Fortifications were irregular, it having five Baſtions and four Curtains of unproportionable length. In the mouth of the Harbour the greateſt part of the Parapets were wanting; nor had the Foſſé either breadth or depth ſufficient, being without any falſe Bray, and with the Counterſcarp ruined. There was no covered way; and the natural ſcituation
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:102362:59"/>
of the place was extreme defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, not onely by reaſon of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral eminences of ground which commanded the Ramparts of the Town, but of certain Vallies by which a whole Army might march up to the very Foſſé co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the hills from any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. So that when it was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed ſome years before, by skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Captains and Enginiers, they concluded it indefenſible againſt any great Army, without a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of ſtrong Out-works, and at leaſt a Gariſon of four thouſand men to defend it. Beſides theſe inconveniencies, a great part of the Artillery was diſmounted, and there were neither Beds nor Wheels to be found for the great Ordnance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:102362:59"/>In ſo great defect of all things, and with ſo ſmall a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Defendants, was Canea inveſted with a great Army abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly provided with Artillery and all other inſtruments of death; with a vaſt number of Pioniers, by which means they incredibly advanced their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches; and adding Art to Power, made abundance of arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Fires, to hide their men as they worked, from the ſight of the Town. And at the ſame time they beat Drums and Kettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drums, and ſet up Tents in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places where they had no Souldiers, to make the Gariſon ſpend the ſhot of their Cannon and Muskets in the air, and ſhoot at places where there was no body to hurt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:102362:60"/>About three days after their landing, the Enemy began the firſt Battery with ſix pieces of Cannon; and in two days more, they had raiſed three other Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, with which they continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beat ſeveral parts of the City; which was more and more infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, as the Turks advanced their Approaches, with Musket-ſhot and Arrows. The Cannon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at firſt did no great effect more than frighten the people with battering down the Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and the Town-houſe; which, by reaſon of their height, were moſt expoſed. But on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the Cannon of the Town did terrible execution up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Enemy; ſo that they had not the courage to attempt an
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102362:60"/>
Eſcalade, though they had brought almoſt all the Oars of their Galleys on ſhore, to make Ladders of.</p>
               <p>It was now eight days ſince the beginning of the Siege, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any news of Succour, and many of the Defendants were already killed and wounded; which gave great apprehenſion to the people, when they conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered how few Souldiers they had, and how thoſe few were already diminiſhed. In the midſt of this perplexity, came Letters from General Cornaro, which aſſured them he was preparing to come in perſon to relieve them, and was now drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the Militia of the whole Kingdom for that purpoſe. But
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:102362:61"/>
Fortune ſoon deluded the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of the General, ſince the new Levyes, when he ſhould have marched on for Canea, moſt cowardly abandoned him; ſo that he was forced to retire to Suda with his own followers.</p>
               <p>At this time, Seignior Angeli making uſe of the ſilence and obſcurity of the night, paſſed with three hundred men through the whole Turkiſh Army; and though they were ſaluted with ſhowrs of ſhot as they went got well into Canea. But this Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour was far inferiour to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of the place, which had already loſt more than this Relief ſupplied; ſo that their number ſtill diminiſhing, they could make no Sallies upon the Enemy, who
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:102362:61"/>
were now with their Approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches come neer the Foſsé. But when Seignior Angeli was got in, who by his authority, being Major of the Gariſon, had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſeveral differences in the Town, it was propoſed by the Officers to make a Salley, that they might ſee the Works of the Enemy. This was done with that vigour, that they penetrated into the Turk's Trenches, ſlew many, and put more of them to flight; and came back into the City with great ſpoils, and no loſs. But deſiring afterwards to try their fortune again, they found the Enemy better upon their guard, and return'd with nothing but blows. So that conſidering the condition they
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:102362:62"/>
were in, and what ſcarcity there was of Defendants, they did not onely reſolve to make no more Sallyes, but to abandon the Half-Moon, and draw all their men into the Town, to defend the Walls. And now Canea began mightily to be ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: for the Turks being come to the Foſſé of the Baſtion of St. Demetrius, fell on raiſing earth about the Counterſcarp; which Wert, the chief Engienier in the Town, thinking to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb them in, made two Mines below, but with no ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>Whileſt things went on thus by Land, the Turkiſh Fleet at St. Teodoro did ſend out moſt of their Gallyes every morning towards Capo Spada, to make
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:102362:62"/>
diſcoveries at Sea; ſo that from the other ſide any Veſſels might have come from Suda to Canea with ſafety. And indeed, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagiero every day wrote to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pello Commander of the great Ships which lay at Suda, Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him for Succour. But Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pello, whether it were that he had no mind to expoſe himſelf to an engagement with the Turks, as ſome accuſed him; or that really it was his opinion, as he pretended, that the preſerving of Suda was of more importance than the ſuccouring of Canea, he would never be prevailed with to ſtir. Though the Town was now much preſſed, it was not ſo ſhut up, but that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged found ways, either with
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:102362:63"/>
ſmall Boats, or expert Swim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, who knew all the Creeks upon the Coaſt, to adviſe Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Cornaro of their danger, and of the wants they were in not onely of Souldiers, but of Pioniers, and Gunners, and of Beds and Wheels for their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery; but above all, of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, of which there was a daily conſumption. And becauſe they had not Mortar-pieces for their Bombs, and that it would be too long to ſtay for them from Candia, they invented ſome of Wood, bound about with Hoops of Iron, which did great ſervice, though they laſted but a little while. But as there was a penury of all neceſſarys in the Town, ſo was there a vaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:102362:63"/>
in the Turkiſh Camp; and there was not a day that there did not arrive Veſſels from ſome part or other of that vaſt Empire, either with Men, or Victuals, or Ammunition, for the ſervice of the Leaguer. For Candia lies ſo in the Turkiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, that from ſome place or other Veſſels might come there with any wind. The diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and diſtreſſes of the Town more and more increaſing, Nava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giero ſent Vincent Michele, a noble Venetian, and Chancellor of Candia, to inform General Cornaro of the condition Canea was in, and of the neceſſity there was of a conſiderable and preſent ſuccour. Upon which Cornaro reſolved to diſpatch thither
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:102362:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Count Fenarolo, one of his chief Officers, with three hundred pay'd Souldiers, and five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Bands of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who are called there the Carnides; and twelve Cannoniers commanded by Benedict Canale a young Gentleman of Venice of great expectation, who carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him three thouſand Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quins for the Souldiers. As they came neer the Enemies Trenches, where they ſhould have paſſed with all the ſilence that might be, the Country-Bands, who were but ill diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, made ſuch a noiſe, that they awaked the Turks; who ſtood to their Arms, and preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted them. Count Fenarolo, who led the Vantguard, bravely
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:102362:64"/>
charged through, and with a few men with him got into the Town. But young Canale, whilſt he was fighting with his Sword in his hand, was moſt traiterouſly murdered by one of his own Servants, who ſtripped him of his Chicquines, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ran over to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, where he met with that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice which he fled from. For the Selectar Baſſa being inform'd of the treachery of this Villain, had ſo great a deteſtation of him, that he commanded him to be put to death.</p>
               <p>Navagiero underſtanding that there were ſeveral Companies of Albaneſe in the Turkiſh Camp who had formerly ſerved under the State of Venice, and not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:102362:65"/>
thinking themſelves well dealt with at their Disbanding had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Conditions under the Turk, thought to try if by Rewards he could gain them back. And meeting with one in his Gariſon of their Countrymen who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to carry his Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them, he offered to ſettle better pay upon them than they had under the Turk, if they would return to the Service of the Republick; and to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them to it, he obliged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that every man ſhould have over and above his pay Ten Crowns a piece for a gratuity. But the Albaneſe would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this offer, for fear of ruining their Relations and Kindred who lived in the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Territories.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="120-151" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:102362:65"/>This attempt of putting in Succours by land having ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo unfortunately, there were Letters immediately ſent to the General, to make known the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable condition of the Town, and to preſs him to ſend away the great Ships and Galleys which lay at Suda for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. To this the General an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that it was againſt the opinion of Capello, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Ships, to adventure them for Canea, and leave Suda expoſed; and that ſince the Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dataries and all the Militia of the Kingdom were not able to relieve the place, how ſhould he alone do it? This Anſwer being come, the Proveditor and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour called a Councel of War,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:102362:66"/>
and communicated it to them; who all concurred to write once more to General Cornaro, to conjure him to ſend them ſuccour; with a Proteſtation that they had done their duty, and that if the place were not preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, it muſt fall. Upon this, Cornaro, being ſtimulated to it by Malipiero Proveditor of Suda, who was for adventuring all to ſave Canea, reſolved to ſend another ſuccour of five hundred men by Land, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the ſame Count Fena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolo, who in Turkiſh Habit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed himſelf through the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Guards, out of Canea to Suda, to haſten Relief, and to offer himſelf to conduct ſuch men as ſhould be ready. And at the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:102362:66"/>
ſame time Conaro intending to try what might be done at Sea, commanded three hundred men to be put upon three Galleys, with Ammunition, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things as the Town moſt wanted, with order to endeavour to paſs through the Turkiſh Fleet, and land their Succours. Upon theſe three Galleys, as Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and as Hoſtages of greater ſuccours, were three of the chief Gentlemen of the State of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice; young Cornaro the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals Son, Barbaro Badoaro, and George Moroſini, who comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Squadron. Cornaro was of a Family which had brought a Kingdom to their Country, by the reſignation of Katerina Cornaro Queen of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:102362:67"/>
Badoaro was of the Houſe of Participatio, who had been Hereditary Dukes of Venice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Common-wealth was ſetled in that form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it now is. And Moroſini was no leſs Illuſtrious than either of the other, as being of a Houſe in which there have been ſeveral Princes of their Country, four Ducheſſes of Venice, three Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, two Queens, five Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs whereof one of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, four and twenty Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curators of St. Mark, and eleven Captain-Generals.</p>
               <p>The ſeventeenth of July, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobard, a Captain of great name, with three hundred choſen men, Sallyed out of the Town into the Trenches to meet the ſuccour:
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:102362:67"/>
and Proveditor Navagiero him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in perſon went to defend the Counterſcarp. And at the ſame time, as had been concerted, Count Fenarolo appeared in ſight of the walls with the ſuccour which he had brought ſo far without any oppoſition. But the Turks who lay in ſome hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes hard by, hearing a noiſe, ſtood to their Arms, and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Venetians, put them in ſome diſorder. Count Fenaro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, who again led the Vantguard, advanced with ſome few, the greateſt part of his men forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him, and many of them leaping into the Sea to avoid the Turkiſh Scymeters; amongſt whom was loſt one of the chief Enginiers in Candia; which was
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:102362:68"/>
fatal to the Town, at a time that they had ſo much need of him for their Mines. Of all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, onely Captain Morat a Frenchman kept his Company together, and brought it entire into the Town. But with that, and all the reſt of the Succour, there got in but two hundred and nine perſons, part of which were wounded. The night after, the three Galleys which Cornaro had ſent from Suda, came before Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea; and it is hard to ſay, whether with greater bravery or ſucceſs paſſed over the Prowes of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Turkiſh Galleys into the Port. But by reaſon of the ſtreightneſs of their Gallies, all they brought with them was two hundred Pioneers, ſome Cheſts
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:102362:68"/>
of Fire-balls, Planks for their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, and fifty thouſand weight of Powder. If the Siege had been raiſed, there could not have been greater joy in the Town, than was at the arrival of this Succour; which was teſtified by loud ſhouts, and firing all their Guns: which the Selectar Baſſa wondring at, asked what was the cauſe of that noiſe in the Town; and being told that there were three Venetian Galleys come in with Succours, he ſent for thoſe who were Captains of the Guards that night, and commanded their Heads to be ſtruck off.</p>
               <p>Theſe Galleys making their way ſo bravely into Canea in ſpight of the Turkiſh Fleet, made men ſee what might have been
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:102362:69"/>
done if all the other Galleys and Ships which vainly waſted their time at Suda, had come with them. But the Venetians had not then tryed the goodneſs of their own Veſſels with the Turks, who were ſo cowed after two or three Battels loſt at Sea, that in the progreſs of the War, they every where fled before the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, and durſt not ſtand them though they were double their number.</p>
               <p>Theſe three Captains with their Galleys being got into the Port, drew their Ciurmes on ſhore, who did extraordinary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; the greateſt part of them being afterwards conſumed in the Siege. And that they might employ their times as uſefully as
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:102362:69"/>
they could, Cornaro undertook the defence of the Baſtion of St. Demetrius, and Badoaro and Moroſini each of them of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Baſtion; ſtanding there day and night, expoſed to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt dangers.</p>
               <p>To hinder the Turks who were now advancing to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of St. Demetrius, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginier Wert made a Gallery in the Foſſé, which as ſoon as he had finiſhed, he found was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſeful, in regard there was no ſtanding there to defend it. So that he was adviſed to ſet it on fire. But whilſt the Officers were debating how to do it, the Turks charg'd them furiouſly, and made themſelves Maſters of the Gallery, with the ſlaughter of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:102362:70"/>
the greateſt part of the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants. And ſo this Gallery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a double damage to them; not onely as they were deprived of it themſelves, but as it proved of uſe and ſervice to the Enemy.</p>
               <p>By this time the Turks had made two Mines in the front of St. Demetrius Baſtion; which the Defendants by their great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence met with, and drove them thence, remaining Maſters of the place. But they were not ſo fortunate in the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of a third Mine; for Wert finding the ground Sandy, and therefore thinking it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the Enemy could make uſe of it, neglected the evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it. But he quickly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the contrary by lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:102362:70"/>
experience; for fire being given to the Mine, with a moſt terrible commotion it tumbled all the flank of the Baſtion into the Foſſé, making a breach wide e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to enter. Whereupon the Turks with many Enſigns ſuddenly marched to the aſſault, which was moſt reſolutely and with much effuſion of bloud ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained by the Defendants, who forced them to pull up the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns which they had planted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Works, and to retire with great loſs and confuſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Trenches. But this ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not without much harm to the Venetians, who loſt Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentini a Corſican Captain &amp; ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others of their beſt Officers; the Proveditor Navagiero, who was in the thickeſt of the danger,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:102362:71"/>
being ſorely hurt with a ſtone. In a word, the Churchmen and the women did wonders in this occaſion. The Wall was not onely ruined with this laſt Mine, but the Parapet fell down; ſo that the Baſtion on that ſide was open for an Aſſault: whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Seignior Broazzo, who had performed all the parts of a good Captain, to encourage his men to follow him, took a Spade in his hand, and began to throw up earth to make up the breach; which he filled up with Buts and Sacks of Earth and Wool. And becauſe they found the Turks at work upon another Mine at the point of the Baſtion, Wert thinking it impoſſible to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it, bethought himſelf of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:102362:71"/>
way, which was, to make a Well above it, that it might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaporate without effect. But before this Well was half made, the earth about it fell in, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Workmen; ſo that then they had no way but to throw in a vaſt quantity of water, which penetrating into the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and moiſtning it, hindred the Mine from taking fire.</p>
               <p>The Enemies finding their Mines not ſo ſucceſsful, betook themſelves again to their Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; in order to which, they filled the Foſſé with Bavins, and made the way even to the Town; and then gave another terrible Aſſault, but were ſtoutly repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Defendants.</p>
               <p>That evening an Arrow was
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:102362:72"/>
ſhot into the Town, with a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it, which ſeemed to come from the Selectar Baſſa to the Governour, inviting him to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver up the Town, and promiſing him good Conditions if he did: but declaring there ſhould be no mercy, if he perſiſted to reſiſt him. The Proveditor ſent away the Letter to the General, and without making any Anſwer to the Enemy, continued to defend the place with his wonted dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. The Selectar Baſſa enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that he had no Anſwer, gave order to prepare againſt the next morning all his Forces both by Land and Sea to give a general Aſſault. Preſently after break of day, threeſcore and ten Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, with a hundred and fifty
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:102362:72"/>
Barks full of Souldiers, appeared before the Port, with deſign that whilſt the Galleys were batter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Town, the Barks ſhould with the Souldiers ſurprize the Mole, and at the ſame time the Land-Army ſhould make an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault in four ſeveral places. The Proveditor did all that man could to animate his Souldiers, though weak and languid with labour and watching: and it happening by the favour of Heaven, that the Sea-Forces could not land by reaſon of a ſtrong wind which blew from ſhore, he turned the force of the whole Gariſon to the defence of the Land-ſide; in which the very Women had a part, who with mighty boldneſs mixed themſelves amongſt the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:102362:73"/>
Souldiers, to defend their Houſes and their Altars. The Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of one of theſe women was moſt remarkable, ſince though ſhe ſaw her Father fall dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her, ſhe never went back till they had quite repulſed the Enemy from the place where ſhe fought. The Turks who came out of their Trenches with Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ladders to aſſault the gate of Saboinera, were ſo plyed with Muſquet-ſhot, that they threw down their Ladders and ran back. They who aſſaulted the gate of Rettimiotta, bore all down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and entred with four Enſignes at the breach; but they were ſo ill treated with the ſhot of the Town, and of the Cannon which thundered upon
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:102362:73"/>
them from the next Baſtion, that they were forced to retreat in that haſt, that they left three of their Enſignes behind them. They who aſſaulted the breach of St. Demetrius finding themſelves expoſed to the Cannon of the Baſtion of St. Salvador, after great ſlaughter of their Men were alſo conſtrained to retire. But they who mounted by the fourth Breach, planted their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and maintained their ground ſome hours; but were at laſt repulſed with ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. As the deſtruction of the Aſſailants was very great, ſo was the loſs of the Defendants; many of their beſt men periſhing in this encounter, and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Albano, and the Captains
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:102362:74"/>
Brocobard and Palma being dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly wounded.</p>
               <p>About this time there was an expectation of Succour from General Molino, who ſent from his Fleet which lay at the three Iſlands four great Ships filled with Souldiers and Ammunition, to relieve Canea. But ſuch was the fate of Candia, that they who had the conducting of theſe Ships, either through Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, or want of judgment, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of taking the right way to Canea, ſayled to the Southward, and came to Giropetra on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the Iſland, where they were at too great a diſtance to have any opportunity of doing ſervice.</p>
               <p>The Turks now came to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:102362:74"/>
their Spades again, and to fall on working new Mines. Whereupon the Proveditor, having no hopes left of ſucceſs, was thinking to ſet fire to the Arſenal, and to ſink the Galleys and Ships which were in the Port, that they might not be of ſervice to the enemy. But before he would do it, he wrote to Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cornaro to acquaint him with his reſolution; who not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the place to be in that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate extremity, or not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to do, returned him no anſwer. But Proveditor Nava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giero, that he might omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which care and prudence could do, finding that a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe which the Enemy had plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Foſſé threatned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:102362:75"/>
ruine to the Town, made a Mine, to ſee if he could break it: which being filled with ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen bags of Powder, ſucceeded ſo fortunately, that upon the firing it blew the Traverſe all in pieces; which the next night was made up again by the vaſt multitude of the Turks, who had ſo many hands to employ, that nothing was difficult to them. The next day the Turks gave fire to a Mine within the breach near the Traverſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a weak Rampart of Earth; which being carryed into the Air by the violence of the fire, fell upon the Defendants who were there, and buryed them all alive: at which the Souldiers upon the Guard were ſtruck
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:102362:75"/>
with that terrour, that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned the Poſt, and two thouſand of the Enemy immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ruſhed through the breach upon the Baſtion, and there planting their Enſigns, made themſelves Maſters of all the retreats into the ſtreets; ſo that now Canea ſeemed irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably loſt.</p>
               <p>But for all this, the beſieged no way diſmayed, marched to the Walls to give the laſt proof of their courage. On the one ſide came the Proveditor, with Seignior Angeli and divers Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; on the other came the Governour Albano, who, though grievouſly wounded, with a Pike in his hand charged the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, being ſeconded by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieli
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:102362:76"/>
Rector of the City, and by Chancellor Michieli, and by Bon the chief Magiſtrate, all noble Venetians. To them came running George Moroſini, and young Cornaro, who did actions ſurpaſſing his age, and carryed back with him as a Trophy of his Valour a Musket-ſhot in his Face. And after all, came the Biſhop of Canea himſelf, to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Combatants with his holy Exhortations, and to give them an example of Chriſtian fortitude. Upon which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants, ſo vigorouſly aſſiſted on all hands, beat the Enemy with infinite ſlaughter from off the Baſtion into the Foſſé, with all the Enſignes that they had planted there. This bloody
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:102362:76"/>
Conflict continued near ſeven hours; all the Gariſon having fought there, and all the Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Army. And ſo great was the ſlaughter of the Turks, that the ground was covered with heaps of their Carkaſſes. On the other ſide, ſuch was the loſs of the Chriſtians, that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the Gariſon periſhed in this Encounter. Albano, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his former hurts, had a wound in his mouth; and one Musket-ſhot in his Arm, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in his ſide. Bon was mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally hurt; Michieli, Brouazzo, and almoſt all the Officers in the Gariſon wounded, as well as the Gentlemen, Citizens, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and all Orders of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:102362:77"/>This Aſſault being over with ſo great deſtruction to both ſides, Wert, unable to walk by reaſon of his many wounds, was carryed in a Chair into the Council-Chamber, where the Governour languiſhing too with his wounds, was already come; and there, in preſence of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, the Proveditor, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, the Counſellors, and chief Magiſtrates of the City, and all the Officers of the Gariſon that were conſiderable, he propoſed, ſince the Breaches were open, and the Ramparts down, ſcarce any Captains or Officers left, their Militia almoſt conſumed, no Powder, the Townſmen and Countrymen cow'd; ſince there was neither hopes of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:102362:77"/>
nor any poſſibility of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, That they would be pleaſed no longer to delay to make Conditions with the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and thereby prevent the ſlaughter of ſo many innocent People: telling them, that it was not onely neceſſary, but that it would be Pious to do it; and that they might have juſtified it by the Laws of War, if they had done it much ſooner. The Governour concurred with him in his opinion, which was appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by all the chief Captains. Onely Proveditor Navagiero op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it, ſaying, they had to do with an Enemy who kept not Faith; ſo that to render the place, would be to deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to death. Wert re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:102362:78"/>
that if they by their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy ſhould ſtand out to no purpoſe, it would be a juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any cruelty the Enemy ſhould uſe to them; who if he did break his Faith, let the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of it fall upon him: That they ought to ſubmit to what God Almighty pleaſed, when they had done all that diſcreet men could do for their preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. But the Proveditor broke off the diſcourſe, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting every man to return to his Poſt, and to do his duty. That night they ſent again to General Cornaro, once more to acquaint him with the miſerable ſtate of the Town, which was without Officers, without Souldiers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Enginiers, and reduced to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:102362:78"/>
the laſt deſperation; and that after this time, they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver write to him more. All night long the Enemy continued their Batteries, to hinder the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged from making up their Ramparts. In the morning Wert returned to renew the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which he had made the evening before; and at the ſame time came Deputys from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty of the Town to Nava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giero, to ſupplicate him, ſince it was the opinion of all the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains that the Town could no longer be defended, their Men and Ammunition being ſpent, and the Enemy lodg'd upon their Ramparts, that he would be pleaſed to have commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, and not expoſe to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:102362:79"/>
the rage of a barbarous Enemy, a People who had ſo freely ſpent their Bloud and Fortunes in the ſervice of their Prince and Country. The Proveditor and all the Officers were touched with pity at this Addreſs, and went away immediately to the Baſtion where George Moroſini commanded, to have his opinion of the buſineſs; who told them that he being ſent thither with three Galleys to Succour the place, when he had done it, ſtayed to defend it; but that now they were deliberating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the rendition of it, he would have nothing to do with that, but leave them to reſolve of what they thought beſt for the Publique ſervice, whilſt he
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:102362:79"/>
would conſider what belonged to him to do for the preſervation of his Galleys.</p>
               <p>The ſame morning the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains came again to the Provedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to preſs him to Treat, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that Malvezzi Maſter of the Fire-works, who had done ſuch important ſervice in the Siege, was newly dead of his wounds. Whereupon the Proveditor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated the Biſhop to Celebrate the Maſs of the Holy Ghoſt, to implore the direction of God in this ſo great tribulation; and calling together all the chief men of the City, that they might have their part in what was trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by the Officers of War, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know if any man there could propoſe any way to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:102362:80"/>
the defence of the place. But the Condition of it was ſo deplorable, that they all cryed out it was no longer to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; and that there was a neceſſity of making ſuddenly ſome Compoſition, unleſs they were reſolved to give their Wives and Children up to be ſlaughtered. Whereupon the Proveditor was fain to conſent that there ſhould be an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in writing drawn up for the Rendition of the place; which was to be ſubſcribed by the Proveditor, Governour, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and all the Military Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers. When this came to be ſigned, the Proveditor was ſo grieved in his Soul to ſee to what a paſs he was reduced, that he
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:102362:80"/>
would have put off the doing of it: thinking to ſet fire to the Arſenal, to ſink the Ships and Galleys in the Port, and ſo break in pieces the Artillery. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceving the Souldiers would not have obeyed him if he had given any ſuch command, nor put a thing in practice which would have deprived them of all hopes of quarter; and conſidering that if through his occaſion not onely the Gariſon but all the People in the Town ſhould have been put to the Sword, it would have been no advantage, but rather a prejudice to his Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and that the ſacrificing of ſo many perſons would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the place; he forbore put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe thoughts in execution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="152-196" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:102362:81"/>After Dinner, the Deputys of the Town came again to preſs the Proveditor to Parley, conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him no longer to expoſe the honour of their Wives and Daughters to a licentious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed Enemy. The Provedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor received them with much courteſy, giving them hopes of what they deſired; but would come to no reſolution, till he had once more ſent to General Cornaro: which he did that night, acquainting him with the deſperate extremity they were in, and that yet he would expect till the next day before he Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to ſee if there could be any hopes of Succour ſent him that night. But receiving no anſwer from Cornaro, and being
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:102362:81"/>
ſummoned again next morning by the Enemy, who were prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for another General Aſſault, and going to give fire to Nine ſeveral Mines, he was at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to command a White Flag to be put out upon the Breach. Upon the ſight of which, immediately the Cannon ceaſed, and they heard a voice ſaying, <hi>What would you have?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then Angeli and Bacchieli went out to Parley, telling the Aga, who asked them what they would have, that they deſired a Ceſſation of Arms of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Baſſa, and that he would be pleaſed to ſend ſome one of Authority into the Town to Treat. Preſently a Ceſſation of Arms was granted, and the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:102362:82"/>
Turks came out of their Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in vaſt numbers upon the Baſtion of St. Demetrius, where they ſate themſelves down upon the ground with ſo profound a ſilence, that in ſuch a multitude there was not one word to be heard: and a Turk who by chance ſhot off his Musket, had immediately his Head ſtruck off. Some ſay that the Turks were reſolved, if the Town had not Treated when it did, to have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Siege, their Army was ſo ſhattered, and their men ſo cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the reſiſtance they had met with. But certain it is, that they much admired the bravery of the Defendants; and Aſſan Baſſa was heard to ſay, <hi>That the great Amurat had never taken Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:102362:82"/>
if there had been ſuch men in it as were in Canea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Ceſſation of Arms being begun, the Aga immediately gave advice of it to the Selectar Baſſa, whoſe Head. Quarters were at St. Conſtantin, where he was lodged in a ſtately Pavilion. Upon notice of the Ceſſation, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectar Baſſa bid them tell them in the Town, that they ſhould make ready Hoſtages to be Caution for the performance of the Treaty; and that for his own part, they ſhould find him diſpoſed to give them all reaſonable ſatisfaction. Within a little time, Bacchieli and Captain Brocobard, men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable amongſt the Chriſtians, paſſed out of the Town into the Camp for Hoſtages, and were
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:102362:83"/>
received there with much courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie At the ſame time came from the Camp to the Town, ſent as Hoſtages by the Selectar Baſſa, Zembis Zaccaia Nephew to the Selectar, and Ibrahim Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga. Zembis came arm'd after the Turkiſh faſhion, attended by two Souldiers arm'd with Swords, Bucklers and Piſtols: Upon his back he had a Veſt of Crimſon-Sattin which reach'd the ground, and upon it a rich Mantle em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered with Gold. He and Ibrahim were not ſuffered to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the City, but had a place prepared for them to ſit in the Caſemats along the walls. Where Zembis declaring that he was the Nephew of the Selectar Baſſa, with great veneration he pulled
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:102362:83"/>
out a Paper with the Imperial Seal, which he ſaid was the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion given by the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior to his Unkle, authorizing him to make what Capitulations he pleaſed; and then told them that he was come from the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectar Baſſa to know what it was that they demanded. Angeli made anſwer, that they deſired a Ceſſation of all Hoſtility for fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days; at the expiration of which time, if no Succour came, they would ſurrender the Town. Zembis replyed, that the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Fleet was ſo far from coming to ſuccour them, that to his cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from Zant to Corfu. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geli replying, that however they might ſtay fifteen days to ſee if
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:102362:84"/>
they would come or no; Zem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſwore a great Oath, that he was ſo ſure that they would not come, that he would engage himſelf, if they did, to change his Religion, and turn Chriſtian: and therefore if they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to propoſe, he would take his leave, and return from whence he came.</p>
               <p>Angeli and the reſt hearing this, thought it beſt no longer to defer Capitulating, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſent away a Draught of what Articles they deſired, to the Electar Baſſa; who required for Hoſtages Proveditor Navagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ero himſelf, and young Cornaro the Generals Son. But Captain Brocobard by his dexterity over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming this difficulty, it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:102362:84"/>
that he and Bachieli ſhould remain Hoſtages as they were, and that there ſhould be added to them Seignior Premarini and Seignior Barozzi, two noble Candiots and Gentlemen of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice; as on the other ſide, there ſhould be four Turks ſent into the City.</p>
               <p>The next morning Zembis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with the Capitulation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them that the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Hoſtages had been brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the Selectar Baſſa. <hi>But I,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>know not with whom I treat, and therefore I deſire that I may ſee your Prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor.</hi> But that the Turks might not diſcover the miſery of the Town, Navagiero came to the place where the Turkiſh Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:102362:85"/>
were kept, but attended with his Guards, and all the pomp he could appear in. Zembis ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him with great Courteſie, took notice that Navagiero ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him much diſturb'd: but, ſaid Zembis, <hi>You ought to ſubmit to the will of God, and comfort your ſelf, ſince you have ſo brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſo long defended Canea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the puiſſant Forces of the Grand Seignior.</hi> Navagiero an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>That the reaſon why he was no better provided to defend the place, and that it was ſo ſoon taken, was the confidence he had, that the Grand Seignior would not have broke the Peace which he had made with the Republick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe given him.</hi> Zem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis not willing to enter into a
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:102362:85"/>
diſcourſe which tended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach his Maſter, ſaid, <hi>Well, for all this, I doubt not but we ſhall yet be friends.</hi> And ſo they took leave for that time, one return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Town, and the other to the Camp. Now the Terms of the Capitulation were theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That Canea ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up within ſix days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That all men of what rank ſoever, who deſired to depart from Canea and the Territory thereof, ſhould have liberty to carry all their Baggage and Perſonal Eſtates with them, without the leaſt mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation; and to leave their real and unmoveable Eſtates to ſuch of their Kindred as they pleaſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That ſuch as would ſtay in Canea, ſhould enjoy their Houſes
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:102362:86"/>
and Lands in the ſame manner as they did under the Venetians, without being obliged to pay any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tax than the ordinary Carag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio which the Subjects of Scio and other places pay, which is the tenth part of their Eſtates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>That in matter of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the People ſhould have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to chooſe them three Judges, by whom the Inhabitants ſhould be Judged according to their own Laws: and in caſe of Appeal, there ſhould be a Turkiſh Judge, who ſhould be reſident there for that purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>That all Religious men, as well Greeks as Latins, ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their Churches, Covents, and Revenews, in the ſame manner as they did under the Venetians;
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:102362:86"/>
and that the Latin Chriſtians ſhould keep a Biſhop after their Rites, and the Greeks another af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theirs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>That the Jewes may live there as they were wont to do, without any Tax or Impoſts but the ordinary Carraggio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe were the principal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles which were granted to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea by the Selectar Baſſa; which, though they much pleaſed at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, were in proceſs of time but ill kept.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe the Selectar pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that the Proveditor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagiero ſhould come in perſon to viſit him and deliver him the Keys of the City, Navagiero be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concerned to decline that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, diſpatched Antonio Zanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolo,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:102362:87"/>
a noble Venetian, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Feudatory Horſe, to the Turkiſh Camp with four Horſes, whereof he ordered him to preſent the two beſt to the Selectar Baſſa, and the other two to the two next General Officers. Zancarolo ſet out of Canea accompany'd with an Aga belonging to Aſſan Baſſa of the Land; and when he came near to the Pavillion of the Selectar Baſſa, who was Generaliſſimo both by Sea and Land, and firſt Page of the Grand Seignior, he ſent word by a Calabrian Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado to the Selectar, that he was there to wait upon him. The Renegado, after he had ſtayed about an hour, returned to Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carolo, and told him he might
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:102362:87"/>
come when he pleaſed: who thereupon walk'd up to a great Tent ſtanding betwixt two leſſer ones. Theſe three Tents were ſurrounded by a deep and broad Ditch, and at the entrance were placed ten Sacres upon woodden Frames, with a pole behind e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them like that of a Coach, to which they might ſet Horſes to draw them with eaſe from place to place. The Ditch was ſet round with a thouſand Archers, all with Turbants and glittering Scymitars; which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the flower of the Army. Theſe Archers had made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Cabins of boughs of Trees neatly interlaced in one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and placed them in that order, that they made a moſt
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:102362:88"/>
delightful ſhew. As Zancarolo approached, they drew from the Ditch, and made Lanes for him to paſs through; every one having an Arrow in his Bow, as if he had been going to ſhoot.</p>
               <p>As he entred the Tent, he found the Selectar Baſſa ſitting Croſs-leg'd upon the ground af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Turkiſh manner, and leaning upon a Cuſhion of Sky-colour'd Velvet embroydered with Gold. He was cloathed with a Sky-colour'd Veſt lined with Ermins, and had a Sword at his ſide ſet with Jewels, the floor being covered with Perſian Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets. He ſeemed to be about thirty years of age; his ſtature was ordinary, his complexion fallow, his eyes black, his beard
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:102362:88"/>
thin, and he looked like a man who was naturally obſtinate and cruel. He was incompaſſed with ſeveral Turks of a Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable preſence, and advanced in years, and moſt of them clothed in fine white Linen. Behind them ſtood eight beautiful Boys in Liverys of Green cloth, holding their hands on croſs. Coming up to the Selectar Baſſa, the Aga who was Zancarolo's Guide fell upon his Knees; and Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carolo preſenting himſelf to him, kiſſed his Veſt: which comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was received by the Sele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctar with very little courteſy. Then Zancarolo told him by an Interpreter, that he was come from the Proveditor of the City to kiſs his hand; who would
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:102362:89"/>
have been now in perſon to have done that Office, but that he was hinder'd by the Gout; and humbly beſeeched him to accept of thoſe two Horſes which he had brought him; which though they were not ſuch as his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſerved, were the beſt that could be found in a beſieged Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The Selectar's anſwer was, that he held himſelf obliged to the Proveditor for his good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that he willingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of his Preſent. At theſe words the Aga roſe up; and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Boys who ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Selectar, they took from under a Carpet a Veſt of Cloth of Gold, and delivered it to the Aga, who gave it to Zancarolo to kiſs, and then put it upon his
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:102362:89"/>
back. After this, he fetched, three other Veſts of leſs value, and preſented them to three Gentlemen who accompanyed Zancarolo. Then he lifted up a Carpet which was at his feet, and taking two handfuls of Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, he gave fifteen to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Horſe, and the reſt amongſt the Grooms who looked to the Horſes.</p>
               <p>Zancarolo when he took his leave, deſired a Paſs, that he might ſafely depart from Canea. But the Selectar anſwered him, that God was one, and his word was one; and bid him go where he would without fear. But ſaid the Selectar, <hi>Why will you go away? I will continue you in your charge of Spaghilar Aga,</hi> that
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:102362:90"/>
is, Commander of the Horſe, <hi>and will be glad of all occaſions to ſee you.</hi> Zancarolo giving him thanks for the honour he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him, told him that he was a Noble Venetian, and could not be wanting to the obligations of his birth. <hi>Raghem,</hi> ſaid the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectar; which is as much as to ſay, <hi>Very well:</hi> and ſo diſmiſſed him.</p>
               <p>The Aga came out to guide Zancarolo further, and making the Turks ſtand off who flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee him, carryed him on purpoſe through a Meadow where lay a number of Heads of Chriſtians lately ſlain; and then led him down into the windings of the Approaches, and thence into the Trenches: A vaſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:102362:90"/>
work, and full of inextri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Labyrinths, containing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſubterraneous Rooms, Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Alleys, through which their Souldiers could paſs cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Cannon and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-ſhot of the City.</p>
               <p>Through this way the Aga conducted Zancarolo to Aſſan Baſſa his Tent, who had about him a number of Janizaries; and in his company was the Aga of the Janizaries himſelf. This Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan was a little old man, of a ruddy complexion, of a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and jovial countenance, and a very cunning politick man. He wore a Crimſon Veſt with ſtreight ſleeves, and a Turbant of the ſame colour. When Zancarolo preſented himſelf to him, the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:102362:91"/>
Aga fell upon his Knees as he had done to the Selectar Baſſa, and Zancarolo kiſs'd his Veſt. But Aſſan received him in another manner than the Selectar had done: for riſing from a Bench where he ſate, and not upon the ground, as the Turks uſe to do, he kiſſed Zancarolo's forehead, and made him ſit down by him; telling him, that he took moſt kindly the Horſe which he had brought him, and thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf much obliged to the Prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor, eſteeming more the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the giver, than the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the gift; and that he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome good occaſion to requite his Excellence for this honour he had done him. Then he made them bring in two Silver Cups a
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:102362:91"/>
moſt delicious Drink; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting one of them to Zanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolo, would have him drink firſt; which he with many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements refuſing, at laſt Aſſan began; who fanned Zancarolo all the while he was pledging him, with the wing of a Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, expreſſing great ſatisfaction in ſeeing him. From thence Zancarolo went to the Spaghitar Aga, and preſented him the fourth Horſe. This Aga was a young man of no Civility, but in appearance proud, treacherous, and cruel.</p>
               <p>In the Articles of the Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, it was agreed, for the convenience of thoſe who would go away, that the Turkiſh Fleet ſhould retire to San Teodoro,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:102362:92"/>
and the Land-Army withdraw farther off the Town. But this was not executed; and when the Captain Baſſa was moved to do it, he anſwered, that he did not mean to draw off his Armies both by Land and Sea for ſix days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, thereby to make way for the Venetians from Suda and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places to clap Succour into the Town; but that they in the Town ſhould make ready to march out at the ſame time both by Land and Sea, and give him notice of it; and then to make way for their more convenient paſſing, he would draw off his Armies on all ſides.</p>
               <p>Hereupon they began to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark the Arms and Ammunition, and ſick and wounded people,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:102362:92"/>
with their Fire-works, and all that the ſtreightneſs of the time would permit them to carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And order was given the tenth of Auguſt to ſuch as were ſound and able to walk, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves to march out under the Conduct of Seignior Angeli by Land: of which at the ſame time they adviſed the Captain Baſſa, deſiring him to withdraw his Army and his Fleet as he had promiſed; to which he returned anſwer, that it ſhould be done. But the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gariſon, when they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the Armies ſhould have been drawn off, and the Coaſts clear, perceived upon the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the guards of the Galleys and ſhips doubled, and upon the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:102362:93"/>
Land-ſide the Army drawn up in Battel about the City in the form of a Half-Moon with the points drawing together, as if they intended to incloſe the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, as they marched out. This ſudden alteration, with the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage which was ſent them by the Captain Baſſa to march out, for he would march in, gave them a reaſonable jealouſie that the Turks would break their Faith, and either put them all to the Sword, or make them Slaves. Hereupon Moroſini ran to his Galleys, intending to get out to Sea, or to dye in the attempt. And Navagiero and Albano in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to leave a memory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them to poſterity, and with their Swords in their hands to ſell
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:102362:93"/>
their Lives as dear as they could. But the retiring of the Turkiſh Fleet and Army preſently diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated this umbrage: whereupon the three Galleys ſail'd away for Suda; and at the ſame time that the Galleys put to Sea, Segnior Angeli marched out by Land with the remains of the Gariſon, which did not amount to five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</p>
               <p>It was a ſpectacle of aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Turks, when they ſaw that they who had reſiſted them were but ſuch a handful of men, as it was of glory to Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li and his Souldiers to find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo admired by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For the Selectar Baſſa ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Angeli with great courteſie, and did him much reſpect as he
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:102362:94"/>
paſſed, applauding his valour, and giving him two old Aga's for his Guard, and commanding them to be careful of him, and not to leave him and his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers till they were out of danger. And thus ended the Siege of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Canea; which would have ſent the Ottoman Army home with diſgrace, if either the numbers of her men had been equal to their Courage, or that ſhe had been as well ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured as ſhe was defended.</p>
               <p>The Selectar Baſſa in the mean time had the leſs ſatisfaction in his Victory, becauſe it had coſt him ſo much blood; and that he apprehended in his abſence his Competitors at Court might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent things to his diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:102362:94"/>
and poſſeſs Ibrahim that he had been too prodigal of his men. Therefore as ſoon as he had taken order for the repairing of the ruines of the Siege, and putting the place in defence, he picked out ſeveral of the fineſt Boys and moſt beautiful Girls that were in the Town, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning them with rich Veſts and the beſt Cloaths that could be got, ſent them of a Preſent to Ibrahim. The beſt of thoſe which were left, he retained for his own ſervice, making them ſo fine, that they were envyed by their Neighbours; as if good Cloaths could cover the miſeries of Servitude, or that Chains were leſs heavy for being guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Two Churches he turned
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:102362:95"/>
into Moſchees, and filled them with moſt magnificent adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. He gave the Chriſtians Liberty of Conſcience, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf at the beginning with ſuch humanity and mildneſs to them, that they were in no fear of him at all. Inſomuch, that few of the Inhabitants would go away, but reſolved to ſettle themſelves in Canea under their new Maſters. But this gentle Government did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long: for in a little time he return'd to his nature, and ſhewed himſelf a Turk. So that when Gentlemen came to viſit him, as they were fain to do who lived under his power, he would put them to do very mean Offices; ſaying, that the
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:102362:95"/>
neceſſity which there was of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fortifying the Town, would not permit him to make any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of perſons.</p>
               <p>And having it in his thoughts to make himſelf Maſter of Suda, without which Canea was not ſecure, he commanded Premari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no a Gentleman of the Venetian Colony to go thither from him, and to let the Governours of it know that they would do well to deliver it up voluntarily; which if they did, they might be ſure to be well uſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected as prudent Commanders, who knew how to comply with the times, and with the fortune of the Conqueror; but if they did not, they muſt expect to feel the cruel effects of his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:102362:96"/>
Premarino would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelf from ſo unworthy an Embaſſy; but the Selectar telling him that it was his duty as well as his intereſt to obey his new Prince, and threatning him if he did not, the poor Gentleman, for fear of death, at laſt undertook ſo diſhonorable an employment. Imbarquing then upon a Galley he went for Suda, and ſhewed the Commiſſion he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Selectar to Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior Malipiero Proveditor of that place. Malipiero with great gravity told him, that he being intruſted by his Prince with the defence of Suda, would never part with it as long as his Soul was in his Body. And then with a fierce and incenſed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:102362:96"/>
he reproached Premari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no with his unpardonable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in coming upon ſuch a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; telling him, that he was unworthy the name of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, much more of a Noble Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian, which was an Order of men ſo devoted to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. This Anſwer he accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed with a Cannon-ſhot, which broke the ſtem of Premarino's Galley, and put him into great confuſion. But at his return to Canea, the Selectar Baſſa gave him a Scymitar, and two rich Veſts, and other Regalo's, as marks of his favour.</p>
               <p>The Selectar having now ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all things at Canea, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no appearance at preſent of any trouble from the Chriſtians,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:102362:97"/>
prepared to return in Triumph to the Court; firſt taking a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral review of his Army of which he found wanting ſome ſeventeen thouſand men.</p>
               <p>When he came to Scio he met Orders from the Grand Seignior which commanded him to haſten to Conſtantinople, that he might be preſent at the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the Bairan. Upon which he quitted the Army, and imbarking upon a fleet Galley, arrived there eight or nine days before it.</p>
               <p>Never man made his entry with more univerſal applauſe, or was received with higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of reſpect by all people, even by the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior himſelf, who roſe from his
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:102362:97"/>
Throne, and ran to meet him, extolling him to Heaven, and loading him with Praiſes and Promiſes that he would never forget his Services, or ever have any Favourite that ſhould be ſo dear to him as he. But ſee the inſtability of Humane things! In the revolution of a few days, this Favourite, this Conqueror, and Darling of Fortune, by the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of ſome of the women, &amp; the cruelty and ingratitude of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahim, fell into the laſt diſgrace.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing theſe Enemies of his inſinuated to Ibrahim, was, that this great Baſſa of whom his Majeſty made ſuch account, and whoſe name was ſo cryed up by the People, did not take Canea by his own valour and conduct,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:102362:98"/>
but by the bravery of the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pyrats, without whoſe aſſiſtance he had been repulſed with ſhame. When by this invention they had undermined the eſteem which the Grand Seignior had for him, they began to talk of the vaſt riches Iſuf had gotten, how Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea was full of Silver and Gold; and that of ſo mighty a prize as he had met with, he kept all to himſelf, and had not preſented the leaſt part of it to the Sultan his Maſter; ſo that it would be thought weakneſs in his Highneſs if he did not call him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>It was not hard, with ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes as theſe, to work upon the jealous and mutable nature of Ibrahim, eſpecially where there
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:102362:98"/>
was any concern of profit, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt avaritious creature in nature. And now being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with Iſuf, and inclined to quarrel, the firſt thing he took occaſion to reproach him with, was, that he had kept his Faith with the Chriſtians at Canea, who all deſerved to be hanged for their preſumption in reſiſting his Arms. To which Iſuf an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that the Town being rendered upon Articles of War, he thought it neceſſary to make them good, not onely to avoid the infamy of breaking Faith, but to invite other places to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Ottoman Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which if they ſaw Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were not kept, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'d out to deſpair, and never yeild.
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:102362:99"/>
But Ibrahim being brutal, and ignorant, and underſtanding no Reaſon but his own will, was not capable of ſuch arguments; but every time he ſaw him, would cavil at ſome thing or other; and at laſt told him plainly, that he muſt find him ſome money; which if he did not do ſuddenly, he ſhould pay for his diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with his Head. To this Iſuf made no reply, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himſelf from his fury. Some days after he ſent for Iſuf, and with Outrages and Threats commanded him to bring forth his treaſure, declaring that if he did not, he would have him ſtrangled. At this language the Baſſa was ſo diſturbed, that looſing at once both his patience
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:102362:99"/>
and reſpect, he made Ibrahim this Anſwer: <hi>All the Treaſure I have, is the glory of my Actions. As for your menaces, they ſo little move me, that I ſee nothing in the world which can make me deſire to live. But I am not ſurprized at this uſage, when I conſider that I have ſerved a Prince who is a Fool.</hi> Scarce was the words out of his mouth, but the Grand Seignior inflamed with rage and indignation commanded he ſhould be ſtrangled. Being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed away into another room, the new Grand Viſir, who was Iſufs creature, came to him, and intreated him to beg Ibrahim's pardon, which he was confident would be granted him if he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored it. But Iſuf would by
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:102362:100"/>
no perſwaſion be prevailed with to do it, nor to ask any thing but three hours time to ſettle his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; at the end of which he was ſtrangled, devoutly invoking the Name of God as he was dying.</p>
               <p>To this ſad Cataſtrophe came Iſuf Baſſa, having lived thirty five years. He was a man of extraordinary great ſence, vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, courteous, diſcrcet, juſt, and adorn'd with ſuch qualities as made him worthy of a happier end, and of a better Maſter. In a few years he was come to that greatneſs, that he commanded all the Ottoman Empire, and had been one of the greateſt Subjects it ever had, if it had been his fortune to meet with a worthy Prince. As he was on a ſudden
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:102362:100"/>
exalted from nothing to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honours, he was as ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depreſt, and that with the compaſſion of all who knew him, even of him who comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his death. For Ibrahim when his rage was over had a mind to ſee him, and made his Body be brought before him with the Bow-ſtring about his neck. And when he found him warm, hoping he had been alive, he rub'd his feet and his hands, and commanded him to riſe. But when he perceived for certain that he was dead, he fell into ridiculous lamentations, and throwing himſelf upon his Body, kiſs'd him, and call'd him his Child, tormenting himſelf, and ſaying he was deprived of the
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:102362:101"/>
onely perſon who was fit to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern his Empire.</p>
               <p>But it was not long before vengeance fell upon Ibrahim, whoſe mind was ſo mutable and full of contradiction, that it was impoſſible to pleaſe him; rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly covetous, and ſenſeleſly prodigal; ſo that no Treaſure could ſuffice his Expence, nor no Rapine his Avarice: ſo caprici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly cruel, that he was equally terrible to thoſe he lov'd and thoſe he hated. Nor was he onely odious to the People and Souldiers, but even to his own Miniſters and Servants. But that which moſt contributed to his ruine, was the diſcontent of the Janizaries, who mutining that they were not paid, exclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:102362:101"/>
againſt the Emperor, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their ſufferings to his folly in entring into an unjuſt War with the Venetians, in which they ſaid he had not onely wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the Treaſure of the Empire, but the blood of his beſt Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who periſhed every day in the Ditches of Candia.</p>
               <p>At this time the Janizaries were very numerous in Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, there being no leſs than fifteen thouſand of them there, which made them the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent. And it hapned that the Spahyes were as diſcontented as they; ſo that they eaſily agreed to remove the cauſe of their grievance, and to depoſe Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him. The firſt ſtep they made to this, was to demand one of his
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:102362:102"/>
Favourites; which with rage and menaces he refuſed to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them. But finding that would not do, he at laſt gave him up, who was inſtantly torn in pieces. But that was not a Sacrifice ſufficient to appeaſe their fury, which like an enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Sea grew higher and higher; ſome reviling Ibrahim, others crying up Mahomet the now regnant Emperour of the Turks, who was then but ſix years old. The Child in that noiſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion was ſo affrighted, that he fell a crying, and ran towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother room, and Ibrahim after him, with an intention to kill him, that the Janizaries might not ſet him up. But he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the women, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:102362:102"/>
the little Prince from his fury, and put him into the hands of the Janizaries, who immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately placed him upon the Throne; and girding a Sable to his ſide, the chief Enſigne of Majeſty in that Government, proclaimed him Emperour.</p>
               <p>Ibrahim being thus dethroned, the Authors of it could not at firſt agree what to do with his Perſon. Some, out of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Ottoman blood, would not lay hands upon him, but rather have him end his days in priſon. But others, who thought they could not be ſafe till he was dead, not knowing what revolutions might happen, let looſe ſome of the Souldiers upon him, who firſt pull'd him
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:102362:103"/>
down upon the ground, and then ſtrangled him. To this diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous end came Sultan Ibrahim, not having ſo much as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of being pityed, but dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abhorr'd of all men, as an abortive of Nature, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Fortune.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:103"/>
            <head>The INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ADvice given by a Gardiner to Sultan Ibrahim, <hi>Page 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Amurat Emperour of the Turks puts his two Brothers Orcan and Bajazet to death, <hi>p. 4,</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi> Beſiegeth Babylon, <hi>p. 16.</hi> Takes it, <hi>p. 23.</hi> Makes his Entry in Triumph into Conſtantinople, <hi>32,</hi> &amp; <hi>33.</hi> Dyes of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch of drinking, <hi>p. 35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Amurat Aga of the Janizaries, <hi>p. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ambaſſador of France in danger, <hi>66,</hi> &amp; <hi>67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ambaſſador of Perſia impriſoned, <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Angeli paſſeth with <hi>300</hi> men through all the Turkiſh Camp into Canea, <hi>p. 112.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aſſan Baſſa, <hi>p. 87.</hi> his great Courteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>p. 172.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>BAbylon deſcribed, <hi>p. 8.</hi> Taken, <hi>p. 23.</hi> The Gariſon put to the Sword after Quarter given, <hi>p. 24.</hi> Conſequences of the loſs of it, <hi>p. 25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biagio Giuliani Governour of San Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoro, blows up himſelf, with <hi>2000</hi> of the Enemy, <hi>p. 102.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102362:104"/>Boiſbodrant General of the Galleys of Malta ſlain, <hi>p. 58.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>CApello General of the Ships refuſeth to ſuccour Canea. <hi>p. 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Canale a Gentleman of Venice ſlain and pillaged by one of his Servants, <hi>p. 119.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Candia ſcituated betwixt Europe, Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, and Aſia, <hi>p. 96.</hi> Its Qualities and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>p. 97, 98.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Candiots ſurprized at the appearance of the Turks Armada, <hi>p. 99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Canea Beſieged, <hi>109.</hi> Surrendred upon Articles, <hi>161.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cornaro General of Candia, raiſes the Militia of the Kingdom, to relieve Canea, <hi>p. 111.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>DOlfino fetched to Conſtantinople by a Janizary and two Druggermen, <hi>p. 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dominique Ottoman, Son of Ibrahim, <hi>p. 59.</hi> &amp; <hi>60.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>GEneral of Barbary adviſeth to fall upon Candia, <hi>p. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102362:104"/>Georgio Moroſini with three Galleys makes his way through the Turkiſh Fleet into Canea, <hi>p. 126.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gelis Aga as he was ſayling for Rhodes, ſet upon by the Galleys of Malta and ſlain, <hi>p. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Genoueſe offer aſſiſtance to the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſo they may be treated with the ſame reſpect as the Venetians, but rejected, <hi>p. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Georgian Lady taken at Sea and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Malta, <hi>p. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Grand Viſier ſuſpected to be a friend to the Venetians, <hi>p. 72.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>IBrahim impriſoned in a Tower of the Seraglio, <hi>p. 5.</hi> Ordered to be ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>p. 15.</hi> Saved by the Women of the Seraglio, <hi>p. 16.</hi> Saluted Emperour, <hi>p. 36.</hi> Begins his Reign with great Reputation, <hi>p. 39.</hi> Informed by one of the Gardiners of the State of his Affairs, <hi>p. 41.</hi> Grows bloody and uncounſellable, <hi>p. 50.</hi> Deſigns a War againſt Malta, <hi>p. 55.</hi> Is diverted from it by his Miniſters, <hi>p. 61.</hi> Thinks of Invading Sicily, <hi>p. 69.</hi> But reſolves to turn his Arms upon Candia, <hi>p. 72.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102362:105"/>
Hides his deſign with deep diſſimulation, <hi>p. 76.</hi> Makes Iſuf Baſſa General of the Expedition, <hi>p. 82.</hi> Depoſeth the Mufti for being againſt the War, <hi>p. 86.</hi> Owns his breach of Faith, and juſtifies it, <hi>p. 90.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Iſuf goes bare-foot to ſeek his fortune, <hi>p. 2.</hi> Made an under-Gardiner in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio. Gives Intelligence to Ibrahim, <hi>p. 6,</hi> Sent for by the Grand Seignior Expects to be put to death, <hi>p. 47.</hi> Is declared Sele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctar Baſſa, <hi>p. 48.</hi> Made Baſſa of the Sea, <hi>p. 49.</hi> Is weary of the Court and thinks to retire, <hi>p. 50.</hi> Incenſed againſt the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, <hi>p. 54.</hi> Perſwades the War of Candia, <hi>p. 70.</hi> Is made Captain General of the Expedition, <hi>p. 82.</hi> Arrives with his Fleet at Scio, where he hath publick prayers made for his ſucceſs, <hi>p. 86.</hi> Comes to an Anchor before Canea, and lands his Army without oppoſition, <hi>p. 101.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegeth Canea, <hi>109.</hi> Draws together all his Forces both by Land and Sea to give a general aſſault, <hi>p. 134.</hi> After many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes hath the Town delivered him upon Articles, <hi>p. 161.</hi> Takes the moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Boys and Girls in the Town to preſent
<pb facs="tcp:102362:105"/>
to Ibrahim, <hi>p. 179.</hi> ſends to demand Suda, <hi>181.</hi> Returns in triumph to Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>p. 18.</hi> Received with joy by Ibrahim, who riſeth from his Throne to meet him, <hi>p. 18.</hi> Falls into diſgrace, <hi>ibid.</hi> Will not ask his life, and is ſtrangled, <hi>p. 190.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>LIberality of the Sultana to him who brought her news of the taking of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, <hi>p. 27.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>MAlipiero Proveditor of Suda, <hi>p. 122, 182.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mufty declares the War unjuſt, <hi>p. 84.</hi> Is reproved by the Grand Viſier, <hi>p. 85.</hi> And depoſed, <hi>p. 86.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>NAvagiero Proveditor of Canea, takes Turks in diſguiſe ſounding the depth of the Sea before Canea, <hi>p. 77.</hi> His great reſolution, <hi>p. 146, 151, 152.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>OMinous Preſages of the War of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, <hi>p. 94.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>POpe ſends the Venetians five Galleys, and publiſheth a Jubile, <hi>p. 93.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:102362:106"/>
               <item>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>een Regent of France ſends four Fireſhips and <hi>100000</hi> Crowns to aſſiſt the State of Venice, <hi>p. 92.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>RIva Proveditor of Tine, receives the Turkiſh Fleet as friends, and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth them with all ſorts of refreſhments, <hi>p. 90.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>SOranzo Ambaſſador at Conſtantinople, diſcovers that the preparations pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for Malta were deſigned againſt the State of Venice, <hi>p. 77.</hi> Diſſembles with the Captain-General of the Turks, <hi>p. 83.</hi> Is arreſted and made a Priſoner, <hi>p. 91.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Suda demanded by the Selectar Baſſa, <hi>p. 181.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sultana's, who ſaved Ibrahim from being ſtrangled are ſtrangled themſelves by the command of Amurat, <hi>p. 34.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>TArpos King of Arabia waits upon Amurat as he goes for Babylon, <hi>p. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102362:106"/>Trenches of the Turk before Canea, <hi>p. 171.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>VEnetians fearing to come to a Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the Turk, are remiſs in Arming, <hi>p. 79.</hi> Sollicit Succours, <hi>p. 92.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>ZAncarolo ſent from Navagiero with a Preſent to the Selectar Baſſa, <hi>p. 164.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Zembis, Nephew of the Selectar Baſſa ſent for a Hoſtage from the Turkiſh Camp, <hi>p. 156.</hi> His generous deportment to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagiero, <hi>p. 160.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:107"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Robert Kettlewel</hi> at the Hand and Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. THe Meaſures of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Obedience: Or, A Diſcourſe ſhewing what Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is indiſpenſably neceſſary to a Regenerate State, and what Defects are conſiſtent with it, for the Promotion of Piety, and the Peace of Troubled Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. By <hi>John Kettlewel,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Coles-hill</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire,</hi> the ſecond Edition with large Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. In Quarto, price bound 8 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102362:107"/>2. A Journey into <hi>Greece</hi> by Sir <hi>George Wheeler,</hi> in company of Dr. <hi>Spon</hi> of <hi>Lyons,</hi> in ſix Books. Containing, 1. A Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age from <hi>Venice</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> 2. An Account of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the adjacent Places. 3. A Voyage through the <hi>Leſſer Aſia.</hi> 4. A Voyage from <hi>Zant</hi> through ſeveral parts of <hi>Greece,</hi> to <hi>Athens.</hi> 5. An Account of <hi>Athens.</hi> 6. Several Journeys from <hi>Athens</hi> into <hi>Attica, Corinth, Boeotia,</hi> &amp;c. With Variety of Sculptures. In Folio, price bound 15 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>3. A Vindication of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, in Point of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to their Prince, againſt the Calumnies of a Book, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The Life of <hi>Julian,</hi> written by <hi>Ecebolius</hi> the Sophiſt. As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,
<pb facs="tcp:102362:108"/>
The Doctrine of Paſſive O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience cleared, in Defence of Dr. <hi>Hicks;</hi> Together with an Appendix, being a more full and diſtinct Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Thomas Hunt's</hi> Preface and Poſtſcript. Unto all which is added, The Life of <hi>Julian,</hi> enlarged. In O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctavo, price bound 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>4. A Sermon Preached at the <hi>Worceſter</hi>-Feaſt, by <hi>George Walls</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Student of <hi>Christ</hi>-Church, <hi>Oxon.</hi> Quarto, price ſtitcht 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>5. The Treaſures of the Sea, a Sermon preached to the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, by <hi>William Thompſon.</hi> In Quarto, price ſtitcht 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>6. An Help and Exhortation to Worthy Communicating: Or, a Treatiſe deſcribing the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:102362:108"/>
Worthy Reception, Duty and Benefits of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and anſwering the Doubts of Conſcience, and other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which moſt generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Men from it; together with Suitable Devotions added. By <hi>John Kettlewel,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Coles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire.</hi> In Twelves, price bound 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>7. Two hundred Queries Moderately propounded, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of Humane Souls, and its Conformity to the Truth of Chriſtianity. In Octavo, price bound 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6. <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>8. A Sermon Preached at the Church of St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> on <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Tueſday, being the firſt of <hi>April</hi> 1684. Before the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb facs="tcp:102362:109"/>
Sir <hi>Henry Tulſe</hi> Mayor of <hi>London.</hi> By <hi>George Hicks</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in ordinary to his Majeſty. In Quarto, price ſtitcht 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>9. A Spelling Book for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. In twenty fours, price bound 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>10. A Good Subject: Or, the right Teſt of Religion and Loyalty. In a Sermon, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>July</hi> the 17th at the laſt Summer-Aſſizes held at <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> for the County of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> Before the Lord Chief Baron <hi>Mountague,</hi> and Sir <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Holloway,</hi> Knight, <hi>John Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> Eſquire, High Sheriff. By <hi>Lewis Atterbury,</hi> D. D.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:109"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102362:110" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
